<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-09T11:18:05+05:30</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Heart of Reason</title><subtitle>A space for philosophical inquiry and meditative prose</subtitle><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Heart of Reason</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/08/08/welcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Heart of Reason" /><published>2025-08-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/08/08/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2025/08/08/welcome/"><![CDATA[<p>The voyage of philosophical inquiry begins not with certainty, but with the gentle acknowledgment of mystery. In this space, we will explore the landscapes of thought that have captivated minds across millennia – not as distant academic exercises, but as living conversations that continue to shape our understanding of existence.</p>

<h2 id="the-purpose-of-this-space">The Purpose of This Space</h2>

<p>This digital sanctuary exists as a meeting place between ancient wisdom and contemporary insight. Here, philosophical exploration breathes with poetic sensibility, creating a space where ideas can unfold at their natural pace. We resist the modern tendency toward information consumption and instead invite contemplation – the slow, deliberate savoring of thought.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The unexamined life is not worth living. – Socrates</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These words, attributed to Socrates, remind us that philosophy is not merely an intellectual pursuit but a way of being. To question, to wonder, to sit in the discomfort of not-knowing – these are acts of courage that transform our relationship with the world.</p>

<h2 id="an-invitation">An Invitation</h2>

<p>Consider this an open invitation to join a conversation that spans generations. Whether you are new to philosophical inquiry or have spent years in its embrace, your perspective enriches our collective understanding.</p>

<p>In the coming writings, we will explore questions of consciousness, ethics, meaning, and the nature of reality itself. But rather than reaching for definitive answers, we will learn to dwell in the questions themselves, finding value in the journey rather than fixating on destinations.</p>

<p>The heart of reason beats not in rigid systems, but in the living pulse of wonder.</p>

<p>Welcome to the journey.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="introduction" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The voyage of philosophical inquiry begins not with certainty, but with the gentle acknowledgment of mystery. In this space, we will explore the landscapes of thought that have captivated minds across millennia – not as distant academic exercises, but as living conversations that continue to shape our understanding of existence.]]></summary></entry></feed>