<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-21T11:46:49+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Heart of Reason</title><subtitle>A space for philosophical inquiry and meditative prose</subtitle><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Lost Art Of Suffering Part 3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/21/the-lost-art-of-suffering-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lost Art Of Suffering Part 3" /><published>2025-08-21T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/21/the-lost-art-of-suffering-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/21/the-lost-art-of-suffering-3/"><![CDATA[<p>“Let everything happen to you: beauty and terror. Just keep going. No
feeling is final.” – Rainer Maria Rilke</p>

<h1 id="this-is-part-3-of-a-3-part-series-on-the-truth-about-happiness">This is part 3 of a 3 part series on the truth about happiness.</h1>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1528659432556-884cfe1480ef?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwyNHx8Y29udGVtcGxhdGlvbnxlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzI3MzYzNzZ8MA&amp;ixlib.rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="dwarf statue in garden" />
<em>Photo by Dorota Dylka on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>When did our hearts become so busy they forgot how to rest? We live in a
world more ordered than ever, yet something ancient in us still yearns
for wildness, for chaos, for the untamed spaces where life flows freely.
Our inner compass, shaped by millennia of evolution, finds itself
spinning in this digital age—detecting disorder even in our most
carefully constructed order. Our survival instinct is still alive but it
is now being used identify achievement with survival. Where technology
was supposed to make our lives better, it is making our instincts
malfunction.</p>

<p>Like children who’ve outgrown their oldest instincts but haven’t quite
grown into their newest tools, we find ourselves caught between ages.
Our technological advancement races ahead while our consciousness pants
to catch up. There is a level of responsibility and awareness attached
to how technologically advanced we get. With limitless power and no
sense of responsibility we will destroy ourselves. Yet, this is escaping
our awareness because running technology the way it is running seems to
be good for business but bad for humanity. But for how long can we stay
pacified?</p>

<p>So, what are we losing? Maybe, we don’t know because we never really
knew we had it. This strange feeling of living in a hyper-connected
society is precisely what makes us feel like something is missing and
we’re just noticing now. In this rush to smooth out life’s rough edges
we’ve begun to lose something precious—the art of sitting with ourselves
in the quiet spaces between doing.</p>

<h2 id="the-inability-to-contemplate">The inability to contemplate</h2>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1614454542040-a0125d70ba2b?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw4fHxkaXN0cmFjdGlvbnxlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzI4NjIwNTV8MA&amp;ixlib.rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="man in white crew neck shirt wearing black framed eyeglasses holding white tablet computer" />
<em>Photo by Nubelson Fernandes on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>“A man who lies to himself, and believes his own lies, becomes unable to
recognize truth, either in himself or in anyone else, and he ends up
losing respect for himself and for others.” – Fyodor Dostoevsky, “The
Brothers Karamazov”</p>

<p>To suffer is to scrape the sandpaper on our material existence,
revealing the underlying soul in all things. In our digital age, where
every discomfort can be immediately medicated with distraction, we have
lost what Han calls “the contemplative life” – the ability to stay with
our pain long enough to learn from it. He writes: “Pain is a fundamental
experience of negativity that cannot be removed from life. A life
consisting purely of positivity would be unbearable.”</p>

<p>While we shield ourselves from every negative experience, we rush to
transform every moment of discomfort into an “opportunity for growth.”
In this way, we lose something essential to human experience. We
discussed the violence of positivity in the last essay as well as our
modern transparency society. Everything must be visible, measurable, and
positive. “Transparency society eliminates all forms of otherness,” Han
writes. “Everything must be smoothed out and levelled, made transparent.
No resistance is permitted.” This transparency becomes its own form of
violence, an obligation that’s always demanding we constantly perform
our happiness, our success, our optimization. There is no room for
shadow, for depth, for the sacred darkness that gives life its
dimension. Actually, nothing is sacred anymore for all moments of life
can be milked for some kind of gain.</p>

<p>He continues, “The society of transparency is an inferno of the same.”
Yet genuine human experience requires shadow, requires mystery, requires
what Han calls “the negativity of withdrawal”—the ability to remain
hidden, to maintain mystery, to preserve depth.</p>

<p>This brings us to a crucial understanding: the very mechanisms we’ve
created to connect and express ourselves—our digital platforms, our
culture of constant sharing and visibility—may be the very things
preventing genuine human experience.</p>

<p>Martin Buber illuminates this modern disconnection through his concept
of I-It versus I-Thou relationships. Where we once met life as a
‘Thou’ - a living presence to be encountered in its fullness - we now
treat everything, including ourselves, as an ‘It’ - objects to be
analysed, optimized, and used. Yet authentic living requires us to
restore that I-Thou relationship with our own experience, to meet each
moment as a living presence rather than a problem to be solved.</p>

<p>Han says that our phones and screens slowly reshape how we think and
feel, without us even noticing the change. It is a subtle form of power,
programming and controlling us without any defence from our side. This
is a crisis of contemplation, “The loss of the ability to contemplate is
connected to the absolutization of visible, active life. The increase in
the active-hyperactive (no space for the passive) darkens
contemplation’s space of possibility.”</p>

<p>Han proposes this way of being as an alternative to this regime of
enforced positivity and transparency. He continues: “Contemplation is a
form of resistance against the totalizing tendency of the active life.
It opens up spaces of breath and spirit.” This meditative stance
requires what he calls “the gift of listening,” the ability to dwell in
silence and negativity without running away from it and without rushing
to transform it into something productive or positive. Without trying to
make it some kind of spiritual business practice.</p>

<p>The following poem illustrates the kind of attention - unhurried,
unmarked, unmeasured - our souls are starving for.</p>

<p>‘I don’t know exactly what a prayer is.<br />
I do know how to pay attention,<br />
how to fall down into the grass,<br />
how to kneel down in the grass,<br />
how to be idle and blessed…’<br />
– Mary Oliver ‘The Summer Day’</p>

<p>Many indigenous communities still practice collective silence and
ritualized contemplation. The Australian Aboriginal concept of
<em>‘dadirri’</em> - inner deep listening and quiet still awareness - offers a
powerful counterpoint to our culture of constant noise and performance.
These traditions remind us that contemplation isn’t some luxury we’ve
evolved beyond, but an essential human capacity we’re in danger of
losing.</p>

<p>That’s part of the journey forward we need to undertake. In an era of
progress, modernity and technology, if we forget ourselves it is not a
cost we can afford. If we decide to become thinking, conceptual machines
then no matter how advanced we are technologically, we’ll barely be more
alive than the machines that guide us.</p>

<p>“The contemplative life is not passive, but rather a highly active
engagement with negativity. It requires the courage to face the
darkness.” – Byung-Chul Han</p>

<p>In life, caution can be advised more generally than recklessness. But
what if we have erred on the side of too much caution? Then the only
antidote to be prescribed is recklessness, wildness. What is wild is
untameable, uncontrollable and is, for all intents and purposes, free.</p>

<h2 id="do-we-fear-whats-real">Do we fear what’s real?</h2>

<p>“The cure for pain is in the pain.” – Rumi</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1706510568563-4dfe62d2aeb6?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwzM3x8aWxsdXNpb258ZW58MHx8fHwxNzMyNzY1MzM1fDA&amp;ixlib.rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="a woman covering her eyes with her hands" />
<em>Photo by Leila de Haan on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>In this final terrain beyond our assumptions, we must confront a
fundamental truth: authenticity cannot be optimized, measured, or
performed. The contemplative life that Han advocates and the deep
understanding of loss and transformation that Kübler-Ross discovered
through her work with the dying both point to the same revelation – that
our most authentic experiences often arise from what society tells us to
avoid.</p>

<p>Kübler-Ross observed that “The most beautiful people we have known are
those who have known defeat, known suffering, known struggle, known
loss, and have found their way out of those depths…[but] We run away
from the beautiful mystery of death. We hide it behind walls and
flowers.” Similarly, we hide our genuine presence behind walls of
positivity and flowers of refinement.</p>

<p>Han articulates this as a form of resistance. We’ve forgotten how to
simply be. Like children who’ve never learned to sit still, we fidget
through our lives - always reaching for the next task, the next goal,
the next achievement. The simple art of doing nothing has become as
foreign to us as a language we’ve forgotten how to speak. Yet it is
precisely in this ‘doing nothing’, in this ability to stay with our
experience without trying to make something of it, that we find our
authentic being. For our true self is always hiding behind
acceptability, distraction and over-thinking. It is always calling out
for our attention but we refuse to sit with it—with ourselves.</p>

<p>Kübler-Ross’s groundbreaking work with dying patients revealed that
authentic living often emerges from our closest encounters with loss and
mortality. She noted that “Those who learned to know death, rather than
to fear and fight it, become our teachers about life.” This parallels
Han’s observation that “A life that is completely untouched by death is
not life but rather mere survival.”</p>

<h2 id="reclaiming-authentic-experience">Reclaiming authentic experience</h2>

<p>If our senses are thinking and feeling our way through life, should it
not stand to reason that they’re telling us what we need to see and
feel? The constant push for improvement and positivity creates
projections based on our desires. We feel compelled to chase these
desires and avoid those demons but it’s all in our heads. We become
trapped in a world of our mind’s images either running towards or
running away from. A state of being that never allows us to simply be.
Real life, is just beyond that boundary—all we have to do is let our
senses show us what we need to see, to let our feelings bathe us in what
we need to feel.</p>

<p>Both Han and Kübler-Ross, from their distinct vantage points, recognize
that our attempts to sanitize life of its darker aspects ultimately
diminish our capacity for real living. Kübler-Ross noted that “Learning
to live well and to die well are one and the same thing,” while Han
observes that “The society of positivity gives rise to artificial forms
of living that alienate us from the fundamental experience of life,
which also includes negativity, pain and death.”</p>

<p>As we move toward a conclusion, we must recognize that the path forward
isn’t through more improvement, more positivity, or more performance.
The contemplative dimension allows us to experience life in its
fullness—both its light and shadow, its peaks and valleys. It requires
bravery to resist the constant pressure optimize experience and to chase
positivity. It requires us to stand firm in our authentic experience
<strong>especially</strong> when that experience includes pain, doubt, or darkness.</p>

<p>And so, the challenge becomes not how to optimize our experience, but
how to remain authentic in a world that demands performance.</p>

<p>The truth about positivity isn’t that it’s wrong—it’s that it’s
incomplete. Like a painting that uses only bright colours, it lacks the
depth and dimension that shadow provides. As we navigate this
achievement society with its demands for constant enhancement and
performance, perhaps our most radical act can be simply this: to honour
our full spectrum of experience, to resist the violence of enforced
positivity not through more violence, but through what Han calls <strong>“the
contemplative ‘no’”</strong> —a quiet but firm refusal to reduce our human
experience to what can be optimized, measured, or performed.</p>

<p>This no is a refusal to engage in falseness, a refusal to diminish our
experience to the superficial. It is the real protest to stand up to our
right to live full human lives. No one said it wasn’t meant to be scary,
no one said that sadness wasn’t involved—but it was meant to be real.
The more we engage in these forms of violence we’ve discussed, we’re
robbing ourselves of that joy.</p>

<p>For true fulfilment lies not in the desperate chase for happiness or the
anxious avoidance of pain, but in the courage to remain present with
whatever arises, trusting that our hearts—in their infinite wisdom—know
exactly what we need to feel, even when society tells us otherwise.</p>

<p>Simone Weil understood this when she wrote that ‘attention is the rarest
and purest form of generosity.’ She saw that true attention - the kind
that doesn’t seek to change or fix or optimize - is a form of love. ‘The
capacity to give one’s attention to a sufferer is a very rare and
difficult thing,’ she noted, ‘it is almost a miracle; it is a miracle.’
Perhaps this miracle is exactly what our achievement-obsessed culture
needs most.</p>

<p>For, in the end, our hearts beat with both contraction and expansion.
Each beat contains both silence and sound, both pause and movement.
Perhaps this rhythm—not our achievements or our optimizations—is our
truest teacher about how to live: embracing both light and shadow, both
joy and sorrow, both doing and being. For it is in this complete embrace
that we find not just happiness, but something far more precious: <em>our
authentic selves</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In our rush to smooth out life’s rough edges, we’ve begun to lose something precious—the art of sitting with ourselves in the quiet spaces between doing. This essay explores how our society's relentless push for positivity and productivity prevents us from engaging with the contemplative life, a state that allows for genuine human experience, including the necessary shadows of pain and doubt.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why We Can’t Think Beyond Capitalism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/19/capitalist-realism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why We Can’t Think Beyond Capitalism" /><published>2025-08-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/19/capitalist-realism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/19/capitalist-realism/"><![CDATA[<p>We all know this food called pizza. Let’s imagine a scenario where
everyone around you is saying pizza is the only food that exists. It’s
delicious, nutritious enough to keep us healthy, and comes in enough
variations to not get bored of. Everyone around you insists, there’s no
point in thinking of any other foods when we’ve got such an amazing
option. Maybe you feel sick after eating it all the time, each day,
everyday…but people insist we’ve got the best versions of pizza in the
history of all food.</p>

<p>This, ladies and gentlemen, is what Capitalist Realism feels like. We
think we are modern, we think we are free. But in the end, we always
operate within a system as individuals. Capitalism as one such system is
what we are currently involved in.</p>

<p>Joseph Campbell and George Lucas suggest that the nature of all mankind
has always been bound by some kind of organised religion. It gives the
community a sense of order and a sense of purpose. It is not that we are
bound to it or that it controls us, it is that this is in our nature. It
is how we understand our world. But in most cases, the time for being
subservient and deviant vary throughout. For each organised religion
changed and reformed, was discarded and replaced by people not following
it.</p>

<p>So the trend for the early part of our generation and for the major part
of our previous generation has been this thing called capitalism. What
is funny about it is that we now feel that we are the most modern humans
that have existed on this planet. And without conclusive proof stating
otherwise, we seem quite convinced that this is so. But just because we
can’t find it, doesn’t mean the evidence doesn’t exist.</p>

<p>“Compared to cavemen, who were a 1, on the scale of human development we
are a 5. And we think we’ve made it, but we don’t realise that the scale
goes to a million.” – George Lucas</p>

<p><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff8f4a7f0-0e48-4000-95c7-3d04e4efdbb7_1080x859.jpeg" alt="a man holding a green sign in front of a crowd of people" />
<em>Photo by William Gibson on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="capitalist-realism">Capitalist Realism</h2>

<p>An idea put forth by the philosopher Mark Fisher, it is an insightful
take on what happens when society thinks the current alternative is the
best there is. While we might touch on financial aspects, this essay is
more directed towards the social and individual effects of Capitalism.
Fisher described capitalist realism as “the widespread sense that not
only is capitalism the only viable political and economic system, but
also that it is now impossible even to imagine a coherent alternative to
it.”</p>

<p>As Fisher writes in ‘Capitalist Realism’: “Capitalism is what is left
when beliefs have collapsed at the level of ritual or symbolic
elaboration, and all that is left is the consumer-spectator, trudging
through the ruins and the relics.” This haunting description captures
how capitalism survives not through inspiration, but through the
exhaustion of alternatives.</p>

<p>This feeling of ‘stuckness’ is something I relate to. Capitalism and its
goals set for the individual have always made me feel like a failure.
The myth of hard work and pushing oneself to work up the ladder of
meritocracy felt off to me. It was indeed in the boomer generation that
one could truly work themselves up from nothing to buy a house, to have
a decent life and lift themselves out of abject poverty. But now, things
are different.</p>

<p>Workers in the UK, for example, are living with their parents while
drawing a great salary. They are people in their late-twenties, early
thirties. They are saving up to buy a house but the price of houses
keeps increasing—and it’s going up faster than their savings. Then we
have people of the same age but who have inherited a large amount of
money. They’re able to own houses because they already have the capital
available. Not only that but they can employ their surplus capital to
make more money.</p>

<p>We see this financialization playing out dramatically in the food
industry, where massive investment firms now control vast agricultural
lands not to grow food, but to speculate on future prices. Farmers who
once made decisions based on local needs now plant crops based on global
market predictions. Real food—the stuff that keeps us alive and promotes
our wellbeing—becomes abstract numbers on a trading screen, while people
go hungry in a world of plenty. This disconnect between financial
abstractions and physical reality shows how far we’ve strayed from
economic common sense.</p>

<p>Fisher criticised how much finance and the financialization of
everything has come to dominate our economy. Growing financial
instruments, which involve making money from money, are slowly getting
much more popular than producing goods or services. We, who are stuck in
late-stage capitalism, need to fear if this could someday happen. If,
someday, more people were busy with the stock market than growing food.
If, someday, we would need to realise we can’t eat money.</p>

<p>His view was that financialization came with the rise of Neoliberalism –
an ideology that emphasizes free markets, deregulation and
privatization. It was a concerted effort to remove the government
influence from the markets. Neoliberalism emerged in the 1970s as an
economic philosophy championing individual responsibility, free markets,
and minimal government intervention. At its core, it views competition
as the defining characteristic of human relations and redefines citizens
as consumers whose democratic choices are best exercised by buying and
selling.</p>

<p>The belief was that the market is self-regulating and no governing body
can match the self-correcting potential of actual free markets, without
limits. How wrong was that idea. Fisher’s feeling, and of those around
him, was that capitalism was gradually detaching itself from reality and
becoming a ‘virtual’ system that operates according to its own logic
regardless of the consequences of people and planet.</p>

<p>It is also those at the very top of the capitalist system that have much
influence in the direction this takes. I do not think they are malicious
but merely self-serving as most humans are. They are also so
disconnected from the ground-level reality of things—or find this
reality hard to digest—that they do not know the real effects of their
decisions. Over time, we can see the rise of economic inequality and
sadly, also the slow erosion of social solidarity. Where we once
supported each other, now it’s everyone for themselves and we start to
mimic the self-serving behaviour of those we secretly idolize. This has
naturally led to a disappearance of our sense of collective
responsibility—because somehow we believe no one else cares so we don’t
have to either.</p>

<p><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcdc5cd23-ebff-4e8b-a2e6-0eb35945f1c5_1080x849.jpeg" alt="brown concrete building during daytime" />
<em>Photo by Mitch on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="the-mental-health-problem">The Mental Health Problem</h2>

<p>People do care though, they care more than we can know. But we’re all
trapped and need to look out for ourselves. The will to survive is more
primal than the instinct to cooperate. And because there is very little
to give us meaning today, we default to a kind of narcissism that is
very easy to see and everywhere today. We talk about ourselves, we boast
our accomplishments, our desires, our plans for the future and our
beliefs—but secretly I’m sure we doubt all of these things regularly and
heavily.</p>

<p>We can’t change this system alone but we’re too busy building our
personal brands or helping someone else build theirs to even think about
change. We can’t imagine something different because all of this is just
honestly overwhelming. And so, we have the mental health crisis. The
feeling of stuckness, along with the imperative to constantly achieve
and the pressure to perform is slowly eroding something inside us. Just
like capitalism, we’re repeating same old ideas and the ways of doing
things that once felt exciting, but they’re not making us happy anymore.
So, we give up but we keep going.</p>

<p>Fisher suggested that mental health problems should be seen as political
issues and not just personal ones. He argued that the focus on
individual achievement and competition is making people feel isolated
and inadequate, leading to depression and anxiety. The approach of
modern clinical therapy to link these problems to either one’s biology
or brain chemistry or childhood trauma is making all this just about the
individual and not about society. Fisher also wrote, “If it is true that
mental illness is increasing, <strong>it is because of the kind of society we
live in</strong>, not because of some biological or genetic predisposition.”</p>

<p>He pointed out that capitalism often makes us feel like we’re failing
even when we’re not. It sets up unrealistic expectations and then blames
us when we can’t meet them. This can lead to feelings of inadequacy,
anxiety, and depression. He saw this as a form of “<em>reflexive
impotence</em>,” where our belief that we’re powerless actually makes us
less likely to act and change things.</p>

<p>This reflexive impotence becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy – we feel
powerless because we can’t imagine change, and we can’t imagine change
because we feel powerless. It’s a psychological trap that serves
capitalism perfectly: the more defeated we feel, the less likely we are
to challenge the system. Breaking this cycle requires recognizing that
our sense of powerlessness isn’t natural or inevitable. Not at all!
Rather, it’s a learned response to a system that benefits from our
resignation.</p>

<p>One of the main points of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/We-Get-Live-Connected-Everything/dp/B09RLY9CXD">my
book</a>
was to illustrate how we’re connected to everything and that we’re not
isolated individuals on this planet just put here to do work and make
money. While these things are important, there is a larger perspective
we’re often missing. Like the fungus we see in a forest is connected
beneath the ground in a large mycelium network, we’re also connected to
each other by some kind of human Wi-Fi! Although our connections are not
physically visible that doesn’t mean they don’t exist. I can’t see air
but I never claim it doesn’t exist.</p>

<p>Studies on depression have proven that if a patient is moved from their
original environment to one that is calmer, less stressful and offers
more support, they improve. The depression goes away because our
environment affects us deeply, but like a fish in water we’re oblivious
to it. Of course biology plays a role but we can’t just ignore the
impact of socio-economic factors.</p>

<p>Fisher wanted us to understand that our mental well-being is connected
to the wider world and that changing society can be a way to improve our
mental health. In his own words: “It is necessary to reframe the growing
problem of stress (and distress) in capitalist societies. Instead of
treating it as incumbent on individuals to resolve their own
psychological distress, instead, that is, of accepting the vast
privatization of stress that has taken place over the last thirty years,
we need to ask: how has it become acceptable that so many people, and
especially so many young people, are ill?”</p>

<h2 id="the-importance-of-imagination">The Importance of Imagination</h2>

<p>This collective illness points to something deeper than individual
suffering—it reveals the limits of our imagination under capitalism.
When we can’t envision alternatives to our current reality, our minds
become trapped in cycles of hopelessness. The very system that breeds
our anxiety also constrains our ability to imagine solutions. Breaking
free from this mental prison requires us to first acknowledge that our
psychological struggles aren’t just personal failures, but symptoms of a
larger systemic crisis. Only then can we begin to imagine new
possibilities.</p>

<p>To change something in society we have to take action but before we do
that, we have to pause! Pause and cultivate the ability to imagine a
different future. We have to be able to doubt the narratives we’re
getting and start questioning even our assumptions. Because where do
they come from? They come from our environment, from society and the
natural way we take cues from our surroundings while growing up. But if
those cues are now causing sickness, we should be ready to even discard
our deepest held beliefs.</p>

<p>Fisher wrote: “<strong>It’s easier to imagine the end of the world than the
end of capitalism.</strong>” And that’s why it is a powerful idea that has
grasped us so tightly.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1715654177939-2206d89e6e5f?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw2fHxlbmQlMjBvZiUyMHRoZSUyMHdvcmxkfGVufDB8fHx8MTczNjA1MjEzM3ww&amp;ixlib-rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="a large sign that reads the name of the town" />
<em>Photo by Mandy Ferrer on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>I would like to quote a paragraph verbatim from <a href="https://jacobin.com/2018/11/mark-fisher-capitalist-realism-vampires-castle-kpunk">this article from
<em>Jacobin</em>
magazine</a>
:</p>

<p>Yet all around us we see that capitalism engenders misery. In one corner
of the world, white-collar workers languish in grim cubicles, alienated
from their labour, compiling spreadsheets for a multinational
electronics corporation. In another, slum-dwellers melt the discarded
electronics to extract their metal, which they sell for money to eat.
The seas rise and the hills catch on fire, the body breaks and there is
no money for a doctor, and every few years the markets fail, cancelling
the future that a lucky handful of working people have been able to
secure (or so they believed).</p>

<p>The question, then, is <em>why </em>capitalist realism persists, when
conditions under capitalism are so evidently untenable. In “Not Failing
Better, But Fighting to Win,” Fisher wrote:</p>

<p>“In my view it is because it was never really necessarily about the idea
that capitalism was a particularly good system: it was more about
persuading people that it is the only <em>viable</em> system and that the
building of an alternative is impossible… that capitalism is almost like
a force of nature, which cannot be resisted.”</p>

<p>Why he calls this a ‘realism’ is because it mistakes an ideology for
something that is real. It <em>seems</em> real but only because capitalism
excludes the facts that lie outside its ideology, either berating them
or ignoring them entirely. This ideological blindness operates like a
self-fulfilling prophecy—capitalism isn’t just an economic system, but a
lens through which we see reality itself. It shapes what we consider
possible, practical, or even imaginable. When we treat market logic as
natural law rather than human creation, we forget that economics is
meant to serve human needs, not the other way around.</p>

<p>So, in order to extract ourselves from the grips of yet another
historically inaccurate ideology, as human beings regularly must start
looking at the facts. Climate change, mental health and excessive
bureaucracy are some of the highlighted weaknesses of the current
system. The class inequalities, the unsustainable rising of prices and
degradation of culture are some more examples. But I would urge you to
find your own because there is no amount of theory that can replace a
vivid, relevant and real example.</p>

<p>Fisher stressed the importance of collective action. That we must see
ourselves as a globally connected organism, rather than isolated
individuals. We cannot face these challenges alone. He also believed in
“popular modernism” where normal people like you and me become active
participants in shaping our own future rather than just choosing the sad
set of options the market offers. We need a kind of solidarity large
parts of our society may have forgotten.</p>

<p>He spoke of the “<em>collective capacity to dream</em>” and while we are unable
to imagine different futures now, it is imperative that we do. We need
to reawaken those impulses. For if we look around at the world we live
in, this kind of world was once someone’s dream—and we’re living it! Of
course they didn’t dream of the problems and inevitably, any future will
have its problems. We need to first dream and then act. We need to
experiment with different and novel ways of living and in this way, we
will challenge the dominant narratives which are keeping us stuck.</p>

<p>The time we are giving to a future that is making us sick must be
reclaimed. We have to resist the pressure to constantly work and
consume. This, too, is part of what will bring change. We need policies
that prioritize our human well-being and that stops treating us like
machines to be fine-tuned or resources to be exploited. We need to do
something different otherwise we will continue to get what we have
always gotten.</p>

<p>Mark Fisher died tragically by suicide in 2017 after having struggled
with mental health for many years. I would like to thank <a href="https://www.philosophizethis.org/">Stephen
West</a> for introducing me to his work
as his legacy survives and becomes more relevant with each passing year.
His life is a testament to the lack of supportive mental health
circumstances and the importance of challenging what we deem to be
normal and acceptable. Society exists and it must reinvent itself
constantly—especially if we’re wreaking havoc on the planet and our
souls.</p>

<p>We’re all in this together and in our struggle against capitalist
realism, we may remember that hope isn’t just optimism – it’s a form of
resistance. Like Bukowski reminds us in this poem, even in our darkest
moments, there are always possibilities for change, always chances to
reclaim our lives from the machinery of capitalism:</p>

<p>“your life is your life<br />
don’t let it be clubbed into dank submission.<br />
be on the watch.<br />
there are ways out.<br />
there is a light somewhere.<br />
it may not be much light but<br />
it beats the darkness.<br />
be on the watch.<br />
the gods will offer you chances.<br />
know them.<br />
take them.<br />
you can’t beat death but<br />
you can beat death in life, sometimes.<br />
and the more often you learn to do it,<br />
the more light there will be.<br />
your life is your life.<br />
know it while you have it.<br />
you are marvellous<br />
the gods wait to delight<br />
in you.”</p>

<p>― <strong>Charles Bukowski, The Laughing Heart</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This essay explores Mark Fisher's concept of 'Capitalist Realism'—the pervasive sense that capitalism is the only viable system, making it impossible to imagine alternatives. It delves into how this ideology contributes to a mental health crisis by promoting a sense of 'reflexive impotence' and individual failure, and calls for a reawakening of our collective capacity to dream of different futures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A History Of Yoga: The Nature of Reality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/18/a-history-of-yoga-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A History Of Yoga: The Nature of Reality" /><published>2025-08-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/18/a-history-of-yoga-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/18/a-history-of-yoga-part-2/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/flagged/photo-1574787929769-db45db9e4f10?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxMXx8YW5jaWVudCUyMHBoaWxvc29waHl8ZW58MHx8fHwxNzM1MjkyNDg4fDA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="Man sitting beside river painting" />
<em>Photo by British Library on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>Now that we’ve covered what yoga currently is, let’s discover what Yoga
was. To discover this however, we will need to dive a bit deeper into
ancient philosophies of Hinduism and how they influenced each other.</p>

<p>The origins of yoga are unclear but sources say it may have developed
among monks and ascetics in the first millennium BCE—it is only around
this time it is mentioned distinctly from Samkhya. Yoga philosophy is
believed to be first mentioned in the Brihadaranyaka Upanishad, the
oldest Upanishad, and researcher Gavin Flood, translates the experience
of union as, “…having become calm and concentrated, one perceives the
self (atman), within oneself.”</p>

<p>As mentioned in the previous essay, the path in which the mind is still
and the intellect does not waver is called Yoga.</p>

<p>The Yoga school of philosophy is one of the six major schools of Hindu
philosophy. The other five being: Samkhya, Nyaya (justice), Vaisheshika
(perception – inference), Mīmāṃsā (reflection) and Vedanta (conclusion
of the Vedas).</p>

<h2 id="the-nature-of-reality">The Nature of Reality</h2>

<p>Samkhya philosophy believes in the duality of Purusha, consciousness or
witness-consciousness, and Prakriti, matter or nature. Prakriti and
Purusha come into contact with each other and the universe explodes into
the reality we are all very familiar with. The explosion, to be precise,
is into 23 aspects of reality or <em>tattvas</em>.</p>

<p>Some of these are intellect, ego, mind, ears, skin, eyes, tongue, nose,
and the colliding factors that give rise to the five elements—earth,
air, fire, water and space. These range from the abstract to the
concrete. Just as your smartphone contains components from the processor
to the screen that work together to create your user experience, these
23 aspects combine to create our experience of reality. Essentially, the
experience of reality and the ability to think about that experience
emerges from the contact between purusha and prakriti. It is interesting
to note that Samkhya doesn’t explicitly believe in the existence of God.</p>

<p>In Indian philosophy, there were six proofs developed by which anyone
can discern truth. These are:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pratyaksha (Perception):</strong> What you experience directly through
the senses, the most immediate and reliable source. Ex. The feeling
of rain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Anumana (Inference):</strong> What you can logically reason and deduce
based on the facts of your experience. Ex. Wet streets means it must
have rained last night.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Upamana (Analogy):</strong> What you can understand about reality by
relating it to another aspect of reality.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Arthapatti (Postulation):</strong> Based on the above, you can assume the
existence of something, tangible or intangible, to clear up any
confusion.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Anupalabdhi (Non-perception):</strong> Knowing about something through
its absence. If there’s no smoke, then there’s no fire; no trees,
therefore no forest and so on…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Shabda (Reliable Testimony):</strong> Lastly, if someone has already done
all the above properly you should be able to take their word for
it—this refers to enlightened beings as well as scriptures and of
course, peer-reviewed journals.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>While Samkhya accepts three of six proofs, namely direct perception,
inference and reliable testimony, some yoga schools accept all six.
Mostly it is the same three methods of proof that yoga uses too.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1722934804353-0d9f6a55ab5e?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxNnx8YW5jaWVudCUyMGluZGlhfGVufDB8fHx8MTczNTIxNzExOXww&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="A group of stone structures sitting on top of a dirt field" />
<em>Photo by Abhimanyu Shivkumar on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="the-eight-fold-path-ashtanga">The Eight-Fold Path (Ashtanga)</h2>

<p>The yoga school of philosophy, in its essence, is nearly parallel to the
Samkhya school. In their fundamental views of Purush and Prakriti, their
acknowledgement of the three Gunas (Sattva, Rajas and Tamas), their
focus on liberation as the ultimate goal of practice and in the process
overcoming ignorance or <em>avidya</em>, they emerge from the same foundations
and aim towards the same goals. Where they diverge is the common
diversion between theory and practice.</p>

<p>While Samkhya lays the metaphysical framework, outlining the concepts
mentioned above. Yoga builds upon this foundation, offering practical
techniques and a systematic path to achieve the liberation described in
Samkhya.</p>

<p>Patanjali’s Yoga Sutras is one of the foundational sources for Yoga
philosophy, along with Sankara’s Brahmasūtrabhaśya. It was compiled in
the early years of this millennium as the
<em>Pātañjalayogaśāstra</em>—including a treatise of texts where many Indian
scholars of the time wrote their notes and commentary on it. So, in a
way, it was peer-reviewed.</p>

<p>The sutras mention the 8 limbs of Yoga, <em>ashtanga</em>. These are:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Yama (Abstinences or Restraints):</strong> These are ethical things or
acts one should resist or avoid.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Niyamas (Personal observances):</strong> Ethical disciplines directed
towards oneself</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Asana (Posture):</strong> Physical postures practiced in yoga (Postural
Yoga). While modern yoga focuses heavily on asana, in the context of
the 8 limbs, it’s about finding a steady and comfortable seat for
meditation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pranayama (Breath control):</strong> This involves regulating the breath
through various techniques to control prana (vital energy) and calm
the mind.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pratyahara (Sense withdrawal):</strong> Withdrawing the senses from
external distractions and turning inwards to one’s inner self or
chosen deity.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Dharana (Concentration):</strong> Collecting or focusing the mind on a
single point or object.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Dhyana (Meditation):</strong> This is a state of contemplation or
continuous flow of consciousness towards the object of
concentration.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Samadhi (Absorption or Stillness):</strong> The final stage, a state of
complete absorption where the individual consciousness merges with
the universal consciousness. There are different kinds of Samadhi,
some where a person can come back, some where they cannot.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Yoga philosophy says that the entanglement of Purusha with Prakriti is
the root cause of suffering (<em>dukkha</em>) and the cycle of birth and death
(<em>samsara</em>). Isn’t this starting to sound like Buddhism? And so, because
we persist on ignorance (<em>avidya</em>), our consciousness (<em>purusha</em>) starts
to confuse itself with matter (<em>prakriti</em>), mistaking the transient for
the eternal. This leads to attachment, aversion, and a continuous cycle
of desires and disappointments.</p>

<h2 id="the-modern-relevance-of-the-ancient">The Modern Relevance of the Ancient</h2>

<p>It’s a welcome surprise that this issue was at the core of these
philosophies so many centuries ago. Problems that we assume have a
modern source, are more likely the perennial malady of the human being.
We have always desired, we have always suffered in attachment and we
have fluctuated in the spectrum of pleasure and disgust. In so many
ways, nothing has changed.</p>

<p>So, the goal (now and back then) is liberation from all this stuff that
weighs us down. Moksha, the holy grail of yoga practice, is the ultimate
aim. We are told it is like achieving a state of complete freedom and
self-realization. This liberation is not an escape from the world but
rather a shift in perspective, recognizing the true nature of the Self
(with a capital ‘S’) and allowing it to detach from the material realm.
But in all this, moksha does not wish to introduce more separation. Once
liberated, a being can understand the true nature of reality and how the
spiritual and material, like day and night, imply each other.</p>

<p>“The Supreme Good is mokṣha which consists in the permanent
impossibility of the incidence of pain… in the realisation of the Self
as Self pure and simple.” —<em>Samkhyakarika</em> I.3</p>

<p>What’s interesting here is the Samkhya version—it says that it is
actually Prakriti (matter) that binds itself to spirit and so it is not
to free consciousness (purusha) but to free matter itself.</p>

<p>“By seven modes nature binds herself by herself: by one, she releases
(herself), for the soul’s wish” —<em>Samkhyakarika</em> Verse 63</p>

<p>Quite a fascinating take, for we so easily think it is this
consciousness trapped in the body but what if it is the other way
around? What if our body is trapped in this cycle of consciousness and
only slowly releasing itself through life eventually ending in death?
Something to reflect on, an idea that could offer a valuable shift of
perspective.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1461766705442-58d58276121a?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw1fHxtZWRpdGF0aW9ufGVufDB8fHx8MTczNTI5MjE5NXww&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="Concrete statuette" />
<em>Photo by Chris Ensey on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>So to truly practice yoga, we can follow some principles. For our
ethical and moral concerns towards the outer world (<em>Yamas</em>): we should
avoid harming other beings; be honest and truthful; we shouldn’t steal;
we should act with integrity to our environment and social circumstance;
and finally we should not get attached to our possessions and not covet
others’ as well.</p>

<p>Some of these attitudes towards the external world sound very familiar
to those mentioned in the commandments of Christianity, or to
Confucianism and its emphasis on social harmony and ethical conduct.
They naturally share a common element with the Golden Rule, with the
precepts of Buddhism and even some elements of Mayan values and Aztec
philosophy. This is because we humans aren’t that different in the end.
We all do similarly petty things and societies have urged us to
transcend our lower natures and live in harmony with each other. These
fundamental human values do not belong to any religion or culture but to
humanity itself. Therefore, we must remember that this is why societies
have continued to exist and these values are what will help society
survive.</p>

<p>Some inner values we can attempt to adhere to (<em>Niyamas</em>) are:
attempting to be pure in our minds, speech and body; to be content with
oneself and with others, fostering a sense of acceptance of our
individual circumstances; to persevere and persist in our spiritual
practice; to study ourself, to reflect, introspect; and finally to
contemplate the True Self, the greater being, the thing above all things
that reminds one of a greater unity.</p>

<p>Pleasure and pain results from contact of soul, sense, mind and object.
Non-origination of that follows when the mind becomes steady in the
soul. After it, there is non-existence of pain in the embodied soul.
<strong>This is that Yoga</strong>.<br />
— <em>Vaiśeṣika Sūtra 5.2.15–5.2.16</em></p>

<p>Adi Sankara, the 8th century scholar, described the Yoga school of
thought as “Samkhya school with God.” This addition of <em>Ishwara</em> (often
translated as ‘divine consciousness’ or ‘universal spirit’) transforms
yoga from pure philosophy into a living practice. While scholars have
debated Patanjali’s exact meaning of <em>Ishwara</em>, its practical
significance is clear: it represents anything that inspires us to
transcend our limited sense of self.</p>

<p>This transcendence isn’t about escaping reality but about seeing it more
clearly. As the Yoga Vasistha tells us, there are two paths to this
clarity – self-knowledge and the restraint of mental conditioning.
Modern yoga has largely focused on the latter, but both paths lead to
the same destination: a profound understanding of our true nature.</p>

<p><strong>Yoga is the utter transcendence of the mind</strong>. To some, Self-knowledge
through inquiry is difficult, to others Yoga is difficult. But my
conviction is that the path of inquiry is easy for all, because
Self-knowledge is the ever-present truth.— <em>Vasistha to Rama, Yoga
Vasistha 6.1.12–13</em></p>

<p>अथ योगानुशासनम् (atha yogānushāsanam) – ‘Here begins the instruction on
the practice of Yoga,’ writes Patanjali in the opening line of his Yoga
Sutras. These words, written millennia ago, still resonate today. They
remind us that yoga is not just an ancient philosophical system but a
living tradition that continues to evolve and transform. Whether through
physical postures, breath work, meditation, or philosophical inquiry,
yoga offers tools for understanding ourselves and our place in the
universe.</p>

<p>The journey from its ancient roots to its modern expressions shows us
that while methods may change, the essential quest remains the same: to
understand who we are beyond our limited identifications, to find peace
amid life’s inevitable changes, and to realize our connection to
something greater than ourselves.</p>

<p>This understanding of yoga – as both an ancient wisdom tradition and a
living, breathing practice – invites us to engage with it not just as
exercise or philosophy, but as a comprehensive approach to living with
greater awareness and purpose. In this light, every aspect of yoga, from
its philosophical foundations to its practical applications, becomes a
doorway to a deeper understanding of ourselves and our world.</p>

<p>We can build towards a future without being attached to the fruits of
our actions. We can go through life without resorting to control or
frustration when things inevitably change. Not only can we overcome
challenging situations but also recognize our apparent smallness on the
universal scale. Our existential anxiety comes from being a blink in
eternity while yoga reminds us we are eternity as well.</p>

<p>I hope you enjoyed this two-part exposition on Yoga. Stay tuned for more
and please share this with someone who’d be interested in reading this
too.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="yoga" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="hinduism" /><category term="spirituality" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Now that we've covered what yoga currently is, let's discover what Yoga was. To discover this however, we will need to dive a bit deeper into ancient philosophies of Hinduism and how they influenced each other.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A History Of Yoga: The Pizza Effect</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/17/a-history-of-yoga-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A History Of Yoga: The Pizza Effect" /><published>2025-08-17T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/17/a-history-of-yoga-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/17/a-history-of-yoga-part-1/"><![CDATA[<p>From ancient practice to modern movement: How physical culture
transformed an ancient tradition</p>

<p>When I first encountered ‘yoga’ in the West, I felt like a traveller
discovering a familiar landscape transformed into something almost
unrecognizable. It seemed to how I remembered it, how I’d experienced
it. After taking a few classes and bruising muscles I rarely used, I
started avoiding all forms of it in the west. I assumed a kind of
elitism because since I was Indian, I knew what ‘real yoga’ was and this
wasn’t it. But over time I started thinking quite differently about Yoga
and how, maybe none of us, really knew what real Yoga is.</p>

<p>The word Yoga comes from the Indo-European root word <em>yeug-</em>, meaning to
join or to unite. This is the same word at the root of ‘yoke’ and at the
root of <em>yugo</em> in Yugoslavia – the now extinct united nation of the
Slavic people.</p>

<p>So, Yoga was essentially a way to unite body and soul, to join matter to
spirit. It was first and foremost a spiritual practice where the seeker
sought unity. The following line from the Katha Upanishad, written in
around the 1^(st) century BCE, illustrates this well:</p>

<p>यदा पञ्चावतिष्ठन्ते ज्ञानानि मनसा सह ।<br />
बुद्धिश्च न विचेष्टते तामाहुः परमां गतिम् ॥ १० ॥<br />
तां <strong>योग</strong>मिति मन्यन्ते स्थिरामिन्द्रियधारणाम् ।<br />
अप्रमत्तस्तदा भवति <strong>योगो</strong> हि प्रभवाप्ययौ ॥ ११ ॥</p>

<p>Only when <em>Manas</em> (mind) with thoughts and the five senses stand
still,<br />
and when <em>Buddhi</em> (intellect, power to reason) does not waver, that they
call the highest path.<br />
<strong>That is what one calls Yoga</strong>, the stillness of the senses,
concentration of the mind,<br />
It is not thoughtless heedless sluggishness, Yoga is creation and
dissolution.</p>

<p>— <em>Katha Upanishad, 2.6.10–11</em></p>

<p>In part two of this essay we will go into Yoga Philosophy. Here, let’s
explore how recent history led to the popularisation of ‘Postural Yoga’,
or what we’ll call modern yoga.</p>

<p>For most of history, until the end of the 19^(th) century, Yoga in the
form of postures and asanas was seen as a preparation exercise toward
real yoga, which was mainly a meditation practice. The <em>asanas</em> were in
a way, different seats of meditation where the seeker could gain
different insights and perspectives from different postures. The Yoga
Sutras of Patanjali mention them only briefly.</p>

<p>Around 1100 CE, the emergence of Hatha Yoga is recorded. The word
Sanskrit word हठ Hatha, means ‘force’. It was practiced mostly in secret
by yogis in isolation. According to yoga scholar Mark Singleton, Hatha
Yoga’s objectives were to force the vital fluid prana into the central
<em>sushumna</em> channel of the subtle body to raise kundalini energy,
enabling Samadhi (absorption) and ultimately Moksha (liberation).</p>

<p>This sounds almost like a way to hack the system into achieving
liberation, but there’s nothing wrong with trying something new (at the
time). There were very few postures in the yoga compendium and poses
were held for a long time. Even at that time, it was understood by the
yogis that practicing asanas was only a small preparatory part of their
spiritual work.</p>

<p>By the end of the 19^(th) century, Hatha yoga was almost extinct. It was
shunned by both Hindus and the British. But then something changed. Two
men, Yogendra and Kuvalayananda emerged and became the founding fathers
of modern yoga.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1516208398649-d5d401ba8c49?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw0OHx8eW9nYXxlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzQ3NTg5NjF8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="Woman balancing her body on olive-green mat" />
<em>Photo by GMB Fitness on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="the-founding-fathers">The Founding Fathers</h2>

<p>But first, let’s talk about Paramahamsa Madhavadasji (1798-1921). He was
a yogi from Bengal born in 1798 who travelled across India on foot for
almost 35 years. Not much is known about him but he was eager to reduce
the sufferings of the common folk, was an avid practitioner of Yoga and
towards the end of his life taught the secrets of yoga to a select few
and deserving students. According to tradition, he lived to the
remarkable age of 123.</p>

<p>Young Yogendra was a well-educated student who suffered depression in
his youth, at the age of 18. This was in 1916 and seeing him in such a
state, his roommate decided to take him to the Dharamshala of
Paramahamsa Madhavadasji. Despite his suspicion of sadhus, Yogendra took
an immediate liking to Madhavdasji and eventually studied Yoga in his
ashram for more than two years. After leaving the tutelage of his
master, he established The Yoga Institute in Bombay, which is now known
as the oldest organised yoga center in the world.</p>

<p>He travelled to America and Europe very soon after to try and popularise
Yoga there. People who met him noted that he was in many ways already a
westerner, having been educated at St. Xavier’s college in Bombay. To
the west he was a new kind of teacher emerging from the Indian
subcontinent, very unlike swami Vivekananda, often called “a blended
product of the East and West”.</p>

<p>Swami Kuvalayananda was a yoga guru born in 1883. He was from a poor
family but managed to get an education despite his economic limitations.
He was inspired by the emerging desire for Indian independence and was
fierce educator. He met a guru Manikrao who trained him in the Indian
System of physical education, which would form the basis of the type of
yoga he would promote.</p>

<p>In 1919, he met none other than Paramahamsa Madhavadasji and was
inspired by the yogic form of discipline. Joseph S. Alter, an American
medical anthropologist, notes “Though Kuvalayananda was spiritually
inclined and idealistic, he was, at the same time, a strict rationalist.
So, he sought scientific explanations for the various psychophysical
effects of Yoga he experienced.” Combined with his passion for physical
education, his fierce idealism and rational mind, he took on a
scientific approach to understanding Yoga and its processes.</p>

<p>Kuvalayananda started the <em>Kaivalyadhama Health and Yoga Research
Center</em> which still operates in Lonavla, Maharashtra today. Joseph
Alter’s words shed a light on his intentions for his research, “what he
himself had to prove was that this truth [of classical yoga] was based
on natural laws and universal principles. In some sense, pure, objective
science was to be deployed as the handmaiden of spirituality and
orthodox philosophy so as to establish what came to be the theme of his
life’s work”.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1560232657-ffb2e8f5938a?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw0Nnx8Z3ltbmFzdGljc3xlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzQ3NTkwMTF8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="Grayscale photo of woman exercising on top of large rock" />
<em>Photo by Wesley Tingey on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="the-physical-culture-revolution">The Physical Culture Revolution</h2>

<p>We’re almost ready to tie it all together but we have to go back once
more to the west and the origin of ‘<strong>Physical Culture</strong>’—a health and
strength training movement that originated during the 19th century.
During the late 19^(th) century, industrialisation was in full swing.
Workers went to work in shifts and afterwards often led sedentary lives.
German immigrants who had arrived in the United States in the middle of
the century had been promoting ‘German gymnastics’. Even though these
physical education practices became popular, they were held back because
they were ‘non-American’.</p>

<p>But the sedentary lifestyle of white collar workers caused the emergence
of ‘<strong>diseases of affluence’</strong>. These were diseases linked to rising
economic development. Some of these emerging diseases were: type 2
diabetes, asthma, coronary heart disease, cerebrovascular disease,
obesity, hypertension, cancer, alcoholism, gout, and some types of
allergy. So, to combat these diseases, exercises were developed and
promoted.</p>

<p>Physical culture became popular and strength and health-training
programs were ubiquitous in the west. It is not surprising to us now
because we have become normalized to sedentary lifestyles, of working at
our laptops all day. The solutions we use today, to take care of our
health are nutrition and exercise. While these are both valid responses,
it is interesting to understand where this movement came from and what
it was in reaction to. We are stuck in the same socio-economic problem
and are easing the symptoms but not treating the cause.</p>

<p>This convergence of physical culture in the West and India’s emerging
yoga movement created the perfect conditions for transformation.</p>

<p>Yogendra and Kuvalayananda pioneered different aspects of yoga in
pursuit of its revival. In it noted by yoga researcher, Elliott
Goldberg, that Yogendra’s system was “safer, more comprehensive and more
effective” and that he “helped strip hatha yoga of .. what he called
‘mysticism and inertia’”. Yogendra was well educated and had been
emancipated from a need to cling to traditionalism. He wrote many books
on yoga, on poetry and even conducted research.</p>

<p>Kuvalayananda, on the other hand, was a rationalist who saw science as a
way to uncover what yoga had to offer to the world. He cared deeply
about alleviating suffering and used his methods in this pursuit.
Towards the middle of the 20^(th) century, he trained large groups of
yoga teachers in order to spread physical education in India. A strong
India meant a strong Indian nationalism movement. Both men, in the end,
followed their passion and gave the world what they believed it needed.
They remain important men in Indian history and culture.</p>

<p>With the emergence of physical culture in the West, the revival of
Postural Yoga in India and its subsequent export to western nations, we
don’t need to connect the dots too much to see what happened. In India
itself yoga was becoming popular as a tool for the movement of Indian
nationalism. In the past, the postures were described in words from
which a practitioner was meant to understand the flow of the asana. With
the advent of photography, yoga poses could be shown in pictures for the
first time in history.</p>

<p>So, Yoga in its postural form became popular as an exercise, as a weapon
promoting Indian nationalism and as a bridge between philosophy and
spirituality. Ashtanga yoga, Iyengar Yoga, Sivananda Yoga were founded,
each promoting a different philosophy towards the asanas as well as
crafting new variations and technical nuances. One of the medieval forms
of Yoga, which survived in Calcutta, was cultivated by Bishnu Ghosh. The
infamous yoga teacher, Bikram Choudury, founder of Bikram Yoga, falsely
claimed to have learnt directly from Ghosh and began teaching in
America.</p>

<p>So, not only did yoga spread, it became a mix between gymnastics,
occultism and a new-age religion. In today’s world, we see it operating
as a business and since its modern inception it has mainly been an
interest of westerners. A friend who had never visited India remarked to
me once, “So, people in India must be doing yoga all the time, right?” I
could only laugh and tell her “No”.</p>

<h2 id="the-pizza-effect-yogas-global-journey">The Pizza Effect: Yoga’s Global Journey</h2>

<p>This is where we can now understand “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pizza_effect">the pizza
effect</a>”. Austrian
anthropologist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agehananda_Bharati">Agehananda
Bharati</a>, who coined
the term says:</p>

<p><em>“The original pizza was a simple, hot-baked bread without any
trimmings, the staple of the Calabrian and Sicilian contadini
[“peasant-farmers”] from whom well over 90% of all Italo-Americans
descend. After World War I, a highly elaborated dish, the U.S. pizza of
many sizes, flavors, and hues, made its way back to Italy with visiting
kinsfolk from America. The term and the object have acquired a new
meaning and a new status, as well as many new tastes in the land of its
origin, not only in the south, but throughout the length and width of
Italy.”</em></p>

<p>So, after traveling to the West and back, Yoga arrived in India
symbolising something completely different to what it had been in
ancient times. Yoga now had many more postures, some of which had
nothing to do with ancient yoga at all. Yoga scholar Mark Singleton
noted that postures in Niels Bukh’s 1924 Primary Gymnastics resembled
several asanas in modern postural yoga, suggesting that Krishnamacharya,
teacher of B.K.S Iyengar, had been influenced by the gymnastics culture
of his time.</p>

<p>Among Krishnamacharya’s most influential students was Indra Devi, born
Eugenie Peterson in Latvia. As his first female and Western student, she
would become known as ‘The First Lady of Yoga.’ When she opened her yoga
studio in Hollywood in 1947, teaching stars like Greta Garbo and Gloria
Swanson, she helped transform yoga from a male-dominated practice into
something accessible to Western women. Her acceptance by
Krishnamacharya, who initially refused to teach women, marked a pivotal
shift in yoga’s modern evolution.</p>

<p>The scholar Andrea R. Jain agrees with Singleton, noting that posture
“only became prominent in modern yoga in the early twentieth century as
a result of the dialogical exchanges between Indian reformers and
nationalists and Americans and Europeans interested in health and
fitness”</p>

<p><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1bd73189-f5f8-4cfd-b3e9-d001704dee6f_604x202.png" alt="Figure from Primary Gymnastics" />
<em>Figure 1: Photo from Niels Bukh’s Primary Gymnastics 1924</em></p>

<p><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe8c5be62-ecd7-435e-af7c-2a407dde1a9c_380x240.png" alt="Another pose from Primary Gymnastics" />
<em>Figure 2: Another pose from Primary Gymnastics</em></p>

<p>So, we arrive at this point. What is yoga and what was yoga? It is not
an inherently bad thing that yoga has become what it is now. With
research we are seeing there is a plethora of health benefits and people
have noticed significant benefits that are hard to fault. But should we
be misled into thinking this physical exercise system we call yoga has
anything to do with spirituality?</p>

<p>It is most important to note that people will say anything to further
their own purposes. This tendency of human beings is neither insidious
nor evil but merely an instinct in self-preservation. We cannot fault
ourselves for not being well-informed. The roots of yoga go very far
back and what we can see is that in its modern form, it resembles less
and less what it used to be.</p>

<p>“Krishnamacharya’s method, was “a synthesis of several extant methods of
physical training that (prior to this period) would have fallen well
outside any definition of yoga, making use of haṭha yoga, the British
army’s calisthenic exercises, and Niels Bukh’s primary or primitive
gymnastics from Denmark.” – Mark Singleton</p>

<p>The truth of the matter is things evolve, traditions change and systems
are updated. The postural yoga system is no different. We must remember
that while yoga teachers may say the roots of yoga are very ancient, it
is up to us to know that they are only slightly correct. The roots of
postural yoga are more recent than the advent of industrialisation.
Knowing that I wonder if our attitudes towards yoga might change.</p>

<p>This isn’t meant to condemn the practice of Hatha Yoga and it doesn’t
fault the foundations on which all of this was built—the yoga
philosophy. But let’s call a spade a spade. Let’s not pretend to delude
ourselves into thinking these postures will eventually lead to
enlightenment. Let’s not pretend that practicing asanas is bringing us
closer to God. Let’s be realistic, this practice is only a preparation
for a journey that can take us to the depths of what it means to be
human.</p>

<p>This form of yoga has had benefits that are often overlooked. It emerged
as a transnational act during the final stages of colonial rule in India
and as a uniting force that supported Indian nationalism in a time of
dire need. Its popularity has at the very least led people to take up
spirituality as an active part in their lives. Along with offering
healthy exercises, it gave a stimulus to learn more about oneself.</p>

<p>The practice of modern postural yoga can be beneficial to our bodies and
minds. While this is indeed one aspect of yoga, what were the others?
What did the system of yoga initially want to teach and why was it a
spiritual discipline that survived over 2000 years?</p>

<p>In the following essay, we’ll explore the philosophy of Yoga and Samkhya
coming up next week.</p>

<p>For further reading I’d recommend this article by Jill Miller: <a href="https://www.gaiam.com/blogs/discover/are-yoga-poses-ancient-history">Are Yoga
poses ancient
history?</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="society" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="yoga" /><category term="culture" /><category term="spirituality" /><category term="history" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[From ancient practice to modern movement: How physical culture transformed an ancient tradition. When I first encountered 'yoga' in the West, I felt like a traveller discovering a familiar landscape transformed into something almost unrecognizable.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Hidden Cost of Convenience</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/16/modern-consumerism-and-the-shopping-delusion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hidden Cost of Convenience" /><published>2025-08-16T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-16T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/16/modern-consumerism-and-the-shopping-delusion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/16/modern-consumerism-and-the-shopping-delusion/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="how-corporate-practices-and-digital-isolation-feed-our-shopping-addiction">how corporate practices and digital isolation feed our shopping addiction</h2>

<p>In a world where desire meets digital convenience, we find ourselves
caught in an elaborate web of consumption. It’s 2 AM, and someone
somewhere is making a purchase - not because they need to, but because
they can. This isn’t accidental; it’s by design. Former executives from
retail giants like Amazon, Adidas, and Unilever reveal an uncomfortable
truth: our shopping habits are being carefully engineered, our impulses
deliberately targeted, and our awareness of waste systematically
obscured.</p>

<p>The architecture of modern consumerism is built on a foundation of
psychological manipulation, where the distance between desire and
acquisition has been reduced to mere seconds. That was the aim all
along, since Amazon started operations. Now, we willingly participate in
our own exploitation through constant consumption. The system is
designed not just to sell, but to create an environment where buying
becomes our default response to any emotional or social need. (Don’t buy
anything after you realise this. Please.)</p>

<p>But beneath this smooth surface of infinite choice and instant
gratification lies a darker reality. Companies aren’t just selling
products; they’re selling a narrative—one that carefully masks the
environmental and social consequences of our consumption. Did you know
most of the plastic you recycle ends up in landfills? While numbers
vary, 79-85% is buried, 12% is burned and 5-8% is actually recycled. All
the while supermarkets pack everything in plastic, fashion brands launch
up to a million new items annually, electronics are designed to be
irreparable, perfectly usable products are destroyed rather than
donated. Is it too late to ask: <strong>What is the true cost of this
convenience?</strong></p>

<p>The story becomes more complex when we consider how this system
perpetuates global inequalities. The very concept of “third world
countries” – a term that artificially divides our one shared planet –has
become convenient concept for places where our excess can disappear,
where our waste can vanish from sight but not from existence. This
geographical and psychological distance allows us to maintain the
illusion that our consumption habits have no consequences.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1495556650867-99590cea3657?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwzMnx8c2hvcHBpbmclMjB3YXN0ZXxlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzQxMDczODh8MA&amp;ixlib-rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="boy holding cardboard box" />
<em>Photo by Hermes Rivera on Unsplash</em></p>

<p><em>“The cost of a thing is the amount of what I will call life which is
required to be exchanged for it, immediately or in the long run.” –
Henry David Thoreau</em></p>

<h2 id="from-shopping-cart-to-silent-shores">From shopping cart to silent shores</h2>

<p>What Thoreau intuited about the true cost of consumption has become
startlingly literal in our modern world. When we click “buy now,” we set
in motion a chain of consequences that ripple far beyond our immediate
awareness.</p>

<p>These consequences manifest in places like Ghana, where 15 million
pieces of discarded clothing <strong>arrive weekly</strong> in a country that’s home
to just 34 million people. The average American now discards 81.5 pounds
of clothing annually, with only 12% of all textile waste being recycled
globally. The tide carries in our cast-offs, leaving synthetic fibres
and microplastics to strangle marine ecosystems long after we’ve
forgotten about last season’s fashion. This isn’t just a local crisis –
in Chile’s Atacama Desert, a fashion graveyard grows by 39,000 tons
annually, a monument to our excess.</p>

<p>The corporate machine has perfected not just the art of selling, but the
craft of concealment. The waste must be hidden or else we won’t buy!
Take Bath &amp; Body Works, who would rather empty their unsold products
into dumpsters than risk them being used by homeless people – a decision
that reveals how image preservation trumps human dignity in corporate
calculations.</p>

<p>This isn’t an isolated incident but a pattern that repeats across luxury
brands and mass retailers alike. Louis Vuitton destroys $50 million
worth of unsold merchandise annually to maintain brand exclusivity,
while Amazon was caught destroying millions of unsold items in just one
French warehouse - including essential items like face masks and books.
Even furniture giants like IKEA, producing 100,000 pieces daily,
contribute to the 9 million tons of furniture waste entering U.S.
landfills each year. Companies actively destroy usable products, from
designer bags to electronics, all to maintain the illusion of scarcity
and exclusivity.</p>

<p>The technology sector presents perhaps the most egregious example of
engineered obsolescence. In 2024, we’re projected to generate 120
million tonnes of electronic waste globally – devices containing over
62.5 billion dollars’ worth of raw materials, more than the GDP of many
countries. Companies like Apple have made repair not just difficult but
legally dangerous. When iFixIt, a company dedicated to helping people
repair their devices, faces lawsuits for allegedly infringing on
intellectual property, we must question whose interests are really being
protected. The right to repair movement isn’t just about fixing broken
screens; it’s about fixing a broken system that treats
everything—including our planet’s resources—as disposable.</p>

<p>Behind carefully crafted corporate sustainability reports and green
initiatives lies an uncomfortable truth: the waste chain doesn’t end; it
merely shifts geography. In a revealing investigation, electronic waste
from a German recycling depot was traced to Thailand, where workers take
apart devices filled with toxic substances by hand, as they’re exposed
to heavy metals and dangerous chemicals. A single smartphone contains
over 60 different elements, many of them toxic when improperly disposed
of, yet less than 20% of all e-waste is formally recycled.</p>

<p>Perhaps nothing illustrates this global crisis more starkly than the
Great Pacific Garbage Patch, now three times the size of France - a
swirling monument to our throwaway culture, where microplastics from our
clothing mingle with our discarded electronics in an ever-growing soup
of consequences. This is the hidden life exchange Thoreau spoke of—only
now it’s not just our life being exchanged, but the lives of others who
bear the burden of our consumption.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1729747705406-9a32f353873e?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw0NXx8YnV5aW5nJTIwbGlmZXN0eWxlc3xlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzQxMDc0ODd8MA&amp;ixlib-rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="A person holding a cell phone in front of a laptop" />
<em>Photo by Jakub Żerdzicki on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="beyond-the-buy-button-the-deeper-void">Beyond the buy button: The deeper void</h2>

<p>The mountains of waste we generate tell only half the story. The other
half lies in understanding what drives us to consume so compulsively in
the first place. Zygmunt Bauman’s concept of “Liquid Modernity” provides
a compelling framework: we live in an age where everything - including
our own identities - has become fluid, temporary, and disposable. As
traditional forms of community dissolve and long-term commitments become
increasingly rare, we turn to consumption not just for goods, but for
identity and even meaning itself.</p>

<p>This shift from solid to liquid modernity manifests in how we approach
even the most basic aspects of life. We no longer simply buy things; <em>we
buy versions of ourselves</em>. Each purchase promises not just utility but
transformation – a new identity, a fresh start, a better life. The
corporations understand this psychological mechanism all too well. They
aren’t selling products as much as they’re selling possibilities and
lifestyles, each carefully crafted to fill the void left by our
disconnection from traditional sources of meaning and belonging.</p>

<p>Our digital devices, while promising connection, often deepen our
isolation. The same technology that allows us to buy anything at 2 AM
has restructured our social relationships into what sociologist Sherry
Turkle calls “alone together”—physically isolated but digitally
tethered. This digital isolation creates a perfect storm for
consumption: we feel increasingly empty and disconnected, while the
means to temporarily fill that void are literally at our fingertips. The
same screens that separate us from genuine human connection offer
endless opportunities for retail therapy.</p>

<p>Consider how corporations manipulate this vulnerability. When Bath &amp;
Body Works destroys products to avoid association with homeless people,
they’re not just protecting their brand—they’re selling exclusivity, a
form of social distinction that becomes increasingly valuable in a world
where traditional hierarchies and ways of life have dissolved. The
constant flow of new products, from fast fashion to the latest
smartphones, isn’t about meeting genuine needs but about feeding our
anxiety about falling behind in a society where standing still means
sinking.</p>

<p>Yet perhaps most insidiously, this system has convinced us that the
solution to the emptiness it creates lies in more consumption. As
traditional religious and community structures fade, shopping has become
the new religion, and unboxing videos our new rituals. We are, as Bauman
notes, seeking biographical solutions to systemic contradictions –
trying to solve through individual consumption what can only be
addressed through collective transformation.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1597423497965-32b0da69bce3?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxMDN8fHJlcGFpcmluZ3xlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzQxMDc2NTZ8MA&amp;ixlib-rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="white and black electronic devices" />
<em>Photo by Dan Cristian Pădureț on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="the-path-forward-reclaiming-connection-in-a-consumer-world">The path forward: Reclaiming connection in a consumer world</h2>

<p>As we stand amidst the rising tide of our own excess, it’s clear that we
cannot buy our way to meaning, nor consume our way to connection. The
system that created our crisis of consumption is powerful, but not
invincible. Across the world, communities are rediscovering what our
consumer culture made us forget: that the deepest forms of fulfilment
often come not from what we own, but <strong>from what we share.</strong></p>

<p>In Totnes, England, the Transition Town movement has transformed a small
market town into a laboratory for post-consumer living. Their repair
cafés don’t just fix broken toasters; they repair our relationship with
the objects we own. Their tool-sharing libraries remind us that we don’t
each need to own everything we might occasionally use. Most importantly,
these initiatives create spaces where people meet not as consumers, but
as neighbours, collaborators, and friends.</p>

<p>Similar experiments are blooming globally. Copenhagen’s <em>Folkehuset</em>
community centres demonstrate how shared spaces can weave stronger
social fabric than any shopping mall. In Japan, the concept of
“<em>mottainai</em>” – a deep cultural respect for the inherent value of
objects – is finding new relevance in modern repair movements. These
initiatives aren’t just about reducing consumption; they’re about
remembering what it means to be human in a world that increasingly
treats us as mere consumers.</p>

<p>The Dalai Lama’s wisdom rings true here:<br />
“<em>If you think you are too small to make a difference, try sleeping with
a mosquito.</em>”</p>

<p>While systemic change is crucial, we mustn’t underestimate the power of
conscious consumption and community building. When we repair instead of
replace, share instead of hoard, connect instead of consume, we create
micro-models of the world we wish to see. These actions, multiplied
across communities and continents, begin to shift not just behaviours
but beliefs about what constitutes a good life. It will eventually force
corporations to rethink their behaviour.</p>

<p>Individual actions, while seemingly insignificant against the tide of
global consumption, create ripples that extend far beyond our immediate
sphere. Every repair attempted, every unnecessary purchase avoided,
every community initiative supported becomes a small act of resistance
against the narrative that our worth is measured by what we buy.</p>

<p>True change, however, requires more than just individual action. We must
recognize that our crisis of consumption is, at its heart, a crisis of
connection—with ourselves, with the world and with each other. The void
we’re trying to fill with endless purchases can only be filled by
rebuilding the social bonds our consumer culture has eroded. This means
creating spaces and opportunities for genuine human connection, for
sharing not just resources but stories, skills, and time.</p>

<p>The path forward isn’t about returning to some imagined pre-consumer
past, but about actively creating new forms of community that honour
both human needs and planetary boundaries. It’s about recognizing that
the most valuable things in life - friendship, creativity, purpose,
connection - have never been for sale. It requires us to question not
just what we buy, but <strong>what we value</strong>. It calls us to rebuild the
social infrastructure that fast capitalism has eroded - from repair
skills to neighbourhood connections to local economic networks. Perhaps
in this work lies our greatest hope: that as the unsustainability of our
consumer culture becomes increasingly apparent, we might rediscover that
the real treasures of life have been within our reach all along.</p>

<p><strong>Some global waste statistics:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>When H&amp;M rolled out its clothing recycling program promising discounts
for returned garments, investigations found that up to 92% of the
collected items couldn’t actually be recycled</li>
</ul>

<p> </p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>In 2024, we’re projected to generate 120 million tonnes of electronic
waste globally and less than 20% of e-waste is formally recycled</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The value of raw materials in global e-waste is estimated at $62.5
billion annually, more than the GDP of many countries</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A single smartphone contains over 60 different elements, many of which
are toxic when improperly disposed of</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Corporate destruction practices:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Amazon was exposed for destroying millions of unsold items in just one
warehouse in France, including new headphones, books, and face masks</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Louis Vuitton reportedly burned $50 million worth of unsold
merchandise in 2018 to maintain brand exclusivity</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Burberry admitted to destroying $37 million worth of products in 2017
before public outrage forced them to change their policy</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Nike was found to slash and destroy unsold shoes to prevent them from
being resold or donated</p>
  </li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This essay explores the hidden costs of modern consumerism, revealing how corporate practices and digital isolation fuel our shopping addiction. It examines the environmental and social consequences of our consumption, from the mountains of waste in developing countries to the engineered obsolescence of our devices, and questions what we've lost in our pursuit of convenience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Truth About Happiness Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/15/the-truth-about-happiness-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Truth About Happiness Part 2" /><published>2025-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/15/the-truth-about-happiness-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/15/the-truth-about-happiness-2/"><![CDATA[<p><em>“The present-day crisis is not that life has become poorer, less
brilliant, less meaningful, nor that we have less access to happiness
and perfection. Rather, we are suffering from the imperative to be
happy.”<br />
– Byung-Chul Han, “The Burnout Society”</em></p>

<p>This is part 2 of this essay series. We will be examining different forms of violence in modern society through the lens of Byung-Chul Han’s work.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1494537604714-7975224eea63?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwyfHxidXJub3V0fGVufDB8fHx8MTczMjc5MjExM3ww&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="grayscale photography of person laying on ground near bus" />
<em>Photo by D A V I D S O N L U N A on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>What kind of fortune do we seek in this land where schedules whisper
demands and notifications scream for attention? Are we aware of the many
differences that exist between how we must live and how we choose to
live? We have become a society of achievement, where the violence we
inflict upon ourselves exceeds any external force or coercion. The whip
has been internalized, transformed into an endless pursuit of
optimization, productivity, and positivity. We have become, as Han
notes, “achievement-subjects” who exploit themselves willingly, even
enthusiastically.</p>

<p>In the silence between productivity and that task after our next task,
in those rare moments when we pause our relentless self-improvement, we
might glimpse the truth: that we are running from a deeper silence, a
fundamental aspect of human existence that our society has deemed
unacceptable.</p>

<h2 id="the-violence-of-achievement">The Violence of Achievement</h2>

<p>“One of the most dangerous forms violence can take is the compulsion to
do good.” – Simone Weil</p>

<p>Han observes that “the achievement-subject stands free from any external
instance of domination forcing it to work… It is an entrepreneur of
itself. Everyone is master and slave in one.” This entrepreneurship of
the self creates a peculiar form of violence - <em>one that pretends to be
freedom</em>. We are free to optimize ourselves to death, free to pursue
endless self-improvement, free to never be satisfied with who we are.</p>

<p>The modern individual believes they chase achievement and positivity for
themselves. But we all push for positivity because society at some point
commanded it, convinced us it was a worthwhile chase. But those who have
gone past this, and played the game to the end, know it isn’t worth the
effort.</p>

<p>We set ambitious goals and demand that every moment of the day be
productive. Wasting time is a sin. Even in our leisure time, we seem to
aim at some form of achievement in levels of relaxation or
entertainment. We measure everything, to the grams of protein in an egg,
and then we wonder why we eventually get depressed or burnt out. What
about simply experiencing life? What about just being bored?</p>

<p>As Han notes in “The Burnout Society”: “The complaint of the depressive
individual, ‘Nothing is possible,’ can only occur in a society that
thinks, ‘Nothing is impossible.’” We have created a world where the
violence of positivity manifests as an inability to say no, to accept
limits, to embrace negativity as a natural and necessary part of human
existence.</p>

<p>There are complications that arise once people touch elementary
sufferings of being human. They find them wildly uncomfortable. Most
people search harder for distractions and change, seeking an urgent
antidote to their suffering—hoping to regain that perfect and optimized
person. Unable to accept their suffering, they put on a face of victory
as if they have conquered it through their methods.</p>

<p>Once production lines had mindsets that called for continuous
improvement. Now, we do this to ourselves and over time this idea of
perpetual improvement becomes a violence we inflict on ourselves. The
moment we achieve a goal, we set a higher one. The moment we’ve reached
a standard in our lives, that standard goes higher, the margins for
perfection grow tighter. What we don’t realise in all this is that
contentment becomes impossible. It will never be enough and we’re stuck
in a bad loop.</p>

<p>“Nothing is enough to the man for whom enough is too little” – Epicurus.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1507294994578-a3015ffbab52?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw2fHxleGhhdXN0aW9ufGVufDB8fHx8MTczMjc5MjE5N3ww&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="woman wearing white and black sweater sitting on stair" />
<em>Photo by Nick Karvounis on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="the-digital-exhaustion-of-being">The Digital Exhaustion of Being</h2>

<p>“We are all exhausted from our own reflection.” – Jean Baudrillard</p>

<p>In the fog of our struggles, the lifting clouds are always aided by the
mind and its conviction about truth. We are not what the world tells us
we are, and neither are we what our unconscious, inner reality, says we
are. The truth lies somewhere in between, but in our digital age, this
truth becomes increasingly difficult to grasp.</p>

<p>As Han observes, “The digital age is abolishing truth. Even facts are
being replaced by data… The world is becoming progressively more
opaque the more data we gather about it.” It seems that knowing more
about the world has not become revealing but it has become more
blinding—data and statistics blind us to real problems that numbers
cannot quantify.</p>

<p>Along with our misdirected conviction, our current state of being has
evolved into a constant performance—an act of theatre. The digital realm
demands transparency, yet this very transparency becomes a form of
violence. Han notes that “transparency is a neoliberal device… It
serves only to generate information and accelerate communication.”</p>

<p>We find ourselves caught in what he calls the “transparency society,”
where the pressure to be visible, to perform, to share becomes
overwhelming. Couple that with an individual whose sole aim is to
achieve something, anything and then we can see why the rise of social
media influencers has been so prominent. With modern technology, work
schedules and the busy lives we all lead—we’ve become more and more
isolated as individuals who now only ‘feel’ connected through our
devices.</p>

<p>He further notes, “The digital swarm is not a mass. It lacks the unity
that would make it a crowd. Its individuals are isolated unto
themselves.” This isolation manifests in peculiar ways – we’re more
connected than ever, yet increasingly alienated from authentic
experience. We see each other as personas but hardly ever as real human
beings with real human problems, which are wildly similar to ours.</p>

<p>For the isolated individual, sharing is one of the few ways of
connecting but what has caused this isolation in the first place? We’re
all products of a past generation whose interests were status, power and
the glorification of the economy. There is a narrative we’ve grown up
with that keeps us going, keeps us pushing all by ourselves—but to what
end? We seem to be caught in pressures that stem from the outside and
from inside and in our isolation, the digital realm offers the only
chance at connection. But we’re losing something and we don’t even know
what for we rarely have time (or take out time) to think and just
connect with ourselves.</p>

<p>Consider the modern phenomenon of “doom scrolling”: A person lying awake
at 3:00 A.M., exhausted but unable to stop consuming content, responding
to messages, or checking social media. This isn’t mere addiction—it’s a
manifestation of the violence of connectivity. The individual feels
compelled to remain “plugged in” despite physical and mental exhaustion,
fearing that disconnection might mean irrelevance or invisibility in the
digital social sphere. The violence here is in the elimination of
natural rhythms of engagement and withdrawal, replacing them with
constant performance pressure.</p>

<p>As Han points out: “The society of transparency does not allow for any
gaps of information or vision. But both human thought and inspiration
require a void, a gap… Today, there is no longer any intermediary
space for reflection, for quiet contemplation.” This constant
visibility—both to see and be seen—this ceaseless performance of
positivity, creates what he terms “digital exhaustion”—a state where we
are <em>too tired to even recognize our own fatigue</em>.</p>

<p>Jean Baudrillard’s prophetic observation that “We live in a world where
there is more and more information, and less and less meaning” captures
our current predicament very well. In his work <em>“Simulacra and
Simulation,”</em> (which was the philosophical basis for the Matrix movies)
he argues that we have lost touch with reality itself, replacing it with
hyperreality – <em>a simulation that has no original reference point
anymore</em>. He writes: “The virtual world is fabricated to escape from the
real world, not to reflect it. It has no reference in reality anymore.”
This mirrors our current digital existence, where we perform versions of
ourselves that become increasingly detached from any authentic original.</p>

<p>As Han observes, “Digital communication enables immediate response.
Immediacy makes reflection impossible… Respect requires a pathos of
distance. Today, distance is yielding to promiscuous intimacy.” This
collapse of distance that both Baudrillard and Han identify creates what
Baudrillard calls “the desert of the real” – a space where authentic
experience becomes impossible because everything is mediated through
screens and simulations.</p>

<h2 id="the-violence-of-positivity">The Violence of Positivity</h2>

<p>The violence of positivity is the final nail in the coffin where we
experience a systemic denial of negativity. According to Han, this
violence operates by pathologizing normal human emotions like sadness,
doubt, or dissatisfaction, recasting them as problems to be solved
rather than experiences to be lived through.</p>

<p>Someone asked me recently, “Is there something wrong with being happy?
What’s negative about positivity?”</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1680032339010-8141679f3761?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwyfHxmYWtlJTIwc21pbGV8ZW58MHx8fHwxNzMyNzkyMzMwfDA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="a yellow smiley face keychain hanging from the back of a car" />
<em>Photo by Xeriss on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>I said nothing at first, then slowly, an answer came to me. I replied:
There is nothing inherently wrong with being happy. The problem is our
chase for happiness. In that chase, there’s something we desperately try
to avoid, sadness. I mean, if you really look at it, why is there this
desperate desire for an illusory and transitory feeling called
happiness? Why is our culture so obsessed with chasing it, possessing it
and making it our modern God 2.0?</p>

<p>Spiritual traditions of various cultures all speak of the inherent
suffering present in human life. Some say this suffering is itself an
illusion, that can be transcended and some say this suffering is a gift
which is a balm for your soul. Rumi says, the crack is where the light
comes in. So, it may be that we have to be broken open in order to let
our souls fly in this life.</p>

<p>But we are obsessed with painting our outer shells with shines and fake
smiles that tell everyone, everything is okay, it’s fine, it’s awesome.
There’s a darkness in this. When we start to believe that happiness is
all there is in life, its one true goal, then we deny all other things
that exist. When we start putting focus only on positivity we secretly
deny the negativity in life. When we start focusing only on the light we
forget the depth of the dark—not to mention the only time we can enjoy
the beauty of the stars. It is not too different from people who believe
sadness to be the only way of all life. We become, in Han’s words, “too
alive to die, too dead to live”—caught in a weird space where authentic
experience becomes impossible.</p>

<p>If life is just happiness with small respites of sadness, or sadness
with small seductions of happiness—we’re missing the big picture. In
both cases, life is not whole but made to fit in a box that either gives
us security or helps us run away from what we find uncomfortable. We’ve
established how people cannot sit with themselves, let alone their
sadness, their grief. We forget we are all human and grief is a natural
process we have to learn how to feel. But often, unfelt grief and
sadness mutates into a desire to run away from all negative emotion.</p>

<p>What we don’t realise is that we’ve made imaginary distinctions of good
and bad, right and wrong, beautiful and ugly. While there’s nothing
wrong with chasing positive emotion, the toxic part comes when we chase
it <em>at the expense</em> of negative emotion. When we start to deny ‘the
negative’ our life becomes one-sided and hollow. A vase with nothing
inside it, a painting with no depth, words with no soul.</p>

<p>We think giving up on this chase is wrong. We’ve been promised gold at
the end of the rainbow, a reward at the end of the struggle. What we
don’t notice is that we’re actually going through exactly what we’re
trying to avoid but in our minds we’re constantly denying it. In the
chase for positive emotion, we have to inevitably go through negative
emotion but in denial, we refuse to feel it.</p>

<p>That’s really all it asks—to be felt. Have we become so modern that we
do not believe that our grief can bless us, that our sadness can guide
us? My own heart has been broken several times, my illusions shattered
countless times, my idea of self destroyed again and again. But through
all that, I learnt something important—I am none of those things, I am
what survived all that. The essence that persists is the truest reminder
of ourselves we can find. Maybe that’s the blessing in the heart.</p>

<p>For everything we feel, does it not come from the heart? Are we so wise
to tell our heart to allow the excitement but not the depression? If our
senses are thinking and feeling our way through life, should it not
stand to reason that they’re telling us what we need to see and feel?</p>

<p>It is said that denial of negative emotion is also the denial of
positive emotion. If we can’t access our depths we cannot enjoy our
highs. So we become monotone and flat individuals who have already
denied one end the spectrum and slowly end up denying the other as well.
Whether in the chase for happiness or the avoidance of sadness, what
we’re truly afraid of is to feel. To feel the raw strength of our
beating heart that can make us crumble. We’re afraid to feel the simple
silence in which it beats and finally, we’re afraid to face ourselves.</p>

<p>For it’s easier to be fake than real in this maddening world. It’s
easier to deny than to accept ourselves, and each other. The positivity
violence is creating what Han calls “a society without respect
(<em>respectare</em>: to look back).” When we can’t look back, we can’t pause
and we can’t acknowledge the shadow aspects of existence. So, we lose
the ability to truly see ourselves and others.</p>

<p>What then becomes of the authentic self in this desert of simulation? As
Baudrillard warns us, “We are no longer in the drama of alienation, but
in the ecstasy of communication.” This ecstasy, however, leaves us
hollow. We find ourselves yearning for something deeper, something real
– even if that reality includes pain.</p>

<p>We’ll conclude this essay series next week with Part 3. Thanks for
reading and stay tuned.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This essay explores the 'violence of positivity' in our achievement-driven society. It examines how the constant pressure to be happy and productive, as analyzed by philosopher Byung-Chul Han, leads to burnout and a disconnect from our authentic selves, ultimately turning the pursuit of happiness into a source of suffering.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Paradox Of Happiness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/15/the-paradox-of-happiness-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Paradox Of Happiness" /><published>2025-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/15/the-paradox-of-happiness-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/15/the-paradox-of-happiness-1/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-paradox-of-happiness-between-joy-and-suffering---part-1">The Paradox of Happiness: Between Joy and Suffering - Part 1</h1>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Happiness is like a butterfly: the more you chase it, the more it
will elude you, but if you turn your attention to other things, it
will come and sit softly on your shoulder.”</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Henry David Thoreau</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="the-social-aspect-of-happiness">The Social Aspect of Happiness</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“All of humanity’s problems stem from man’s inability to sit quietly
in a room alone.”</p>
  <ul>
    <li>Blaise Pascal</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1505483531331-fc3cf89fd382?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw1MXx8cGVvcGxlJTIwc21pbGluZ3xlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzE3MzExMTd8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="two women holding flowers" />
<em>Photo by Sam McNamara on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>We approach solitude with uncertainty, as if it were some alien task to
master rather than a natural state of being. We run away from it and
fear it, almost as undesirably as boredom. We feel we’d be disconnected
from the world in our solitude but we consider what we would be making
space to connect to. Yet it’s precisely when we accept life’s common
sufferings, solitude among others, that the deepest changes take root
within us. This is why most people seek distractions and change; they
search for an antidote to their suffering—hoping to become some kind of
perfect and happy person.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Men decide far more problems by hate, love, lust, rage, sorrow, joy,
hope, fear, illusion, or some other inward emotion, than by reality,
authority, any legal standard, judicial precedent, or statute.” -
Cicero</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They believe they do it for themselves but if they do not have viewers
to witness their happiness, the effort isn’t worth it—so in reality they
do it for others. Truth be told, most would be more comfortable in
misery, for that is an easier path. Consider the ancient Greek concept
of <em>eudaimonia</em>, which suggests that true happiness comes not from
pleasure or social status, but from living a life of virtue and meaning.
Yet modern society has twisted this notion, making happiness itself the
virtue we must chase.</p>

<p>Feeling above others give happiness this fake allure of being a higher
emotion and thus it is the emotion of the privileged. It is the law of
nature that happiness will always be transient. Most of all it is the
wealthy and privileged who are expected to feel it eternally and
maintain it. How should they do so with such a slippery snake—an
impossible task with such an elusive emotion. This leads them to chase
material solutions: clothes, possessions, and even surgeries that paint
an artificial smile of eternal contentment.</p>

<p>The obligation to be happy in this society that is convenient, affluent
and ever more status driven is something that would break the soul—it is
breaking our souls. Where our true happiness was once found in
community, relationships and familial bonds, we have given these all up
in order to chase the elusive beast of happiness. As the philosopher
Zygmunt Bauman noted, “In a liquid modern life there are no permanent
bonds, and any that we take up for a time must be tied loosely so that
they can be untied again, quickly and as effortlessly as possible, when
circumstances change.”</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Most men pursue pleasure with such breathless haste that they hurry
past it.”<br />
– Søren Kierkegaard</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We all chase happiness because society told us to. We got these ideas
via Bluetooth. We thought it was a worthy pursuit, but those who have
truly attempted it—the ones who have gone beyond and played the
game—know it isn’t worth the effort. Happiness, so ephemeral and
transient, refuses to stay with us. This chase moves forward, realising
that happiness cannot be captured, to find a middle ground where one is
numb to nearly all feeling. Where happiness is no longer happiness, nor
what it used to be and sadness simply refuses to be felt. Thus, we
arrive at a ground where we are numb to all feelings and happy in a fake
exuberance.</p>

<h2 id="joy-versus-happiness-the-prison-of-perpetual-happiness">Joy versus Happiness: The Prison of Perpetual Happiness</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Joy is the serious business of Heaven.” - C.S. Lewis</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1660629465812-1c550d2a2342?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxNXx8aGFwcGluZXNzfGVufDB8fHx8MTczMTcyMjIxMnww&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="a woman on a beach" />
<em>Photo by sandra lansue on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>One must have people to show that one is happy. I doubt being happy
alone by oneself is worth the effort—but being joyful is. Joy, often
confused with happiness, deserves its own consideration. Being in a
state of joy is worth it because it is not dependent on externals and it
is not easy to discern whether a person is in a joyful state of being or
not.</p>

<p>Joy is something that isn’t created but <strong>revealed</strong> and allowed to
flood into our lives as we remove the obstructions to it. Rather than a
state of action or doing, it is a state of being. This is something that
is not easily made into a social requirement. Unlike happiness, joy
cannot be manufactured from activities or their results. It can,
however, emerge from repetitive activity and things that make no sense
but somehow have profound meaning for us personally.</p>

<p>The Buddhist concept of <em>mudita</em>—sympathetic joy—offers an interesting
contrast to our modern pursuit of personal happiness. It suggests
finding joy in others’ happiness rather than constructing our own
artificial euphoria.</p>

<p>For when joyful things are chased like one does with happiness, it
simply spoils the good things in nature and makes them into
resources—ends to be pursued not for the joy they themselves provide but
for their fruits. Creating happiness through experiences that arouse our
emotions and make us feel elated in a kind of surprising way, we feel as
if we may be happy—but truthfully, we cannot be sure.</p>

<p>High arousal emotions distract us from the other side, against emotions
that bring us down low. In these states of ‘high’ we find ourselves, so
to say, ‘on top of the world’. The real shame is why we do not realize
that, regardless of our experience, we always are on top of this world.
The emotions that bring us down make us suffer and we are not being
taught how to deal with suffering, how to make friends with it. We are
simply told to run away from it, to not stay with it or to use our minds
to trick ourselves into ‘thinking positively’.</p>

<p>It is in true suffering that we can experience a kind of joy that feels
confusing to the modern mind but deeply religious to the ancient mind. A
feeling akin to Christian grace or the Hindu concept of <em>Ananda,</em> the
bliss of the compassionate God, this subtle and rich experience is a
revelation of the interconnectedness of these emotions and what their
true and sincere experience leads to.</p>

<p>It is in suffering that the soul shines and finds its truth. And joy,
the state of being, much more worthy than happiness, is something we
allow into ourselves much like suffering. It stands to reason that joy
and suffering are the two ways we see the world, through our own eyes
and those of the mind. Suffering grounds us and joy brings us into
states of wonder, elation, awe and both can be associated with
transcendence.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Out of suffering have emerged the strongest souls; the most massive
characters are seared with scars.” - Kahlil Gibran</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="the-folly-of-the-happiness-chase">The Folly of the Happiness Chase</h2>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1710163132381-5564b0777726?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw0NHx8Y2hhc2luZ3xlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzE3MzA3OTB8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="a man walking down a street past a store front" />
<em>Photo by wu yi on Unsplash</em></p>

<p>We must also wonder about art and if it can ever be fuelled by this
numbing emotion of happiness. The happy person rarely creates, much like
the despairing one. Neither finds anything in the world worth creating
or wondering about. Wonder itself cannot be manufactured like happiness;
it must be revealed. These higher emotions cannot be purchased, forced,
or created—they must emerge naturally from a state of being that
precedes them.</p>

<p>Conceptual thoughts fill a happy person as they descend into frustration
at the obviously absurd attempt to capture an always slipping happiness.
In a strange turn of events, they later welcome despair and depression
for these states finally offer this person respite and a ‘deep rest’
from this exhausting search for happiness.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The search for happiness is one of the chief sources of
unhappiness.” - Eric Hoffer</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Consider the wisdom of the ancient Stoics, particularly Epictetus who
taught that happiness comes not from getting what we want, but from
wanting what we get. Yet modern society has inverted this wisdom,
creating an endless chase for more.</p>

<p>The pursuit of happiness parallels the pursuit of pleasure—both
inevitably lead to pain. The struggle to make these fleeting emotions
permanent and become part of our empty lives reveals the
shortsightedness of modern society’s obsession with progress and
rationality. As philosopher Albert Camus noted, “You will never be happy
if you continue to search for what happiness consists of. You will never
live if you are looking for the meaning of life.”</p>

<p>Few will admit to the emptiness of this search, as doing so means
challenging society itself—something most are unwilling to do since they
derive their identity from it. No one can tell a seeker of happiness
otherwise, for then they are offending them, keeping them from the goal
of submerging themselves in an everlasting sea of positivity. Strangely
enough, even trials and failures will not deter the seeker but only make
their resolve stronger, believing the difficulty of their path is
because the prize is valuable. So they will never admit to the folly and
emptiness of this search, even if they have felt it. To admit that this
search is wrong is to admit society is wrong and to rebuke something
larger than ourselves in such a callous manner is something most people
are not willing to do.</p>

<p>It is normal that most people derive their sense of identity from
society. Only the rare few—those who might seem cursed rather than
privileged—must forge their own identity. Yet in this apparent curse
lies a hidden blessing, a paradox like the privilege of the perpetually
happy person becoming their prison.</p>

<p>This paradox recalls the ancient Zen koan:<br />
A monk asked his master, “What is happiness?”<br />
The master replied, “Grandfather dies, father dies, son dies.”<br />
The monk, confused, asked how this could be happiness.<br />
The master explained, “This is the natural order. Any other way would
bring great suffering.”</p>

<p>In our relentless pursuit of happiness, we have perhaps forgotten what
the ancients knew: that happiness is not a destination but a by-product
of a life well-lived. The modern obsession with happiness has created a
peculiar paradox: the more desperately we chase it, the more it eludes
us. Perhaps true contentment lies not in the chase, but in the
acceptance of life’s full spectrum of experiences, including those
moments of divine discontent that make us uniquely human.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The purpose of life is not to be happy. It is to be useful, to be
honorable, to be compassionate, to have it make some difference that
you have lived and lived well.” - Ralph Waldo Emerson</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This essay delves into the modern paradox of happiness, questioning why society's relentless pursuit of it often leads to dissatisfaction. It distinguishes between fleeting, performative happiness and deep, authentic joy, arguing that true contentment is found not in avoiding suffering but in embracing the full spectrum of human experience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Not Everything Is For Sale</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/14/not-everything-is-for-sale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not Everything Is For Sale" /><published>2025-08-14T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/14/not-everything-is-for-sale</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/14/not-everything-is-for-sale/"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever tried to buy real, pure honey lately? It’s harder than
you’d think. Yesterday, whilst hunting for honey at our local shops, I
stumbled upon a bitter truth about our modern markets—one that’s been
staring us in the face all along.</p>

<p>Real honey isn’t really on the market anymore. So many people want honey
and to fill that demand they made honey mixed with sugar syrup or
jaggery. It has gotten so bad that some honey collectors go to the hives
and come back with this mixed honey—covering their tracks right at the
source.</p>

<p>The numbers tell us the same: according to recent scientific studies,
approximately 75% of honey samples from retail markets worldwide showed
signs of filtration and adulteration. What was once nature’s pure gift
has become another victim of mass production.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1481900369621-54a7facacc6c?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw1fHxob25leXxlbnwwfHx8fDE3MzEyMTM1MzR8MA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="honey raspberry jars" />
<em>Photo by Amelia Bartlett on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="when-pure-becomes-rare-the-hidden-cost-of-demand">When Pure Becomes Rare: The Hidden Cost of Demand</h2>

<p>This made me think—what if we are just living this fantasy that
everything is for sale? Of course there is real honey out there. Of
course one can buy it, but it is getting increasingly harder to find.
The demands of the modern consumerist market are somehow stifling the
production of real things and more fakes are emerging which just fill in
the demand.</p>

<p>The world has changed. Our free market system has now ceased to create
more opportunity but in fact has created more illusion. We thought we’d
be sharing more goods but we’re sharing bad fakes—forced to create bad
fakes in order to make sure the demand doesn’t go to waste. For one
thing our economic system has given us, is this sense “Why not make
money off of this?” Let’s just capitalise on everything, regardless of
ethics. Like bees transforming nectar into honey, we too transform raw
materials into products. But unlike bees, we often compromise the
essence of what we create in service of quantity over quality.</p>

<p>Let’s return to the honey seller. This person’s task of harvesting pure
honey and then selling it at the price agreed by the market isn’t
working out so well. People want 500 jars a month and they can only make
a 100. Of course, they can’t make the bees work overtime. So what does
one do? Their ethics will be guided by their circumstance—they might
have a dependent family, a sick parent or a house in dire need of
repair. So they will meet the demand of 500 jars but by cutting corners.</p>

<p>In the rules of supply and demand that should run economics, this person
should be paid the amount of 500 jars for a 100 jars because there just
isn’t that much supply. Most would disagree because we want our things
at the price we’ve always got them. A little inflation here and there
sneaks under our radars. But let’s look at the honey sellers, they only
have a 100 jars worth of real honey—that’s their limit. If the demand is
at the same price then they have to either choose to meet it by cutting
corners, or just sell a 100 jars and tell 400 people to come next month.</p>

<p>In this way, however, they’re not only selling themselves short, they’re
failing to capitalize on the 400 people at their doorstep willing to pay
for honey. Now, the honey seller thinks, people don’t really know the
difference between real and adulterated honey? So why not, give people
what they want in a way they can’t tell the difference. Most of us have
not worked firsthand with a beehive and eaten pure, raw honey so we
don’t know the difference. We might think we know but we don’t even know
how many times we’ve been fooled in the past by almost-original
products.</p>

<p>Here lies the modern paradox: authenticity becomes a luxury when
survival is at stake. As philosopher Michael Sandel notes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Markets don’t only allocate goods; they also express and promote certain
attitudes toward the goods being exchanged.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What attitudes are we
promoting when we demand nature’s bounty at unnatural prices?</p>

<p>The honey seller’s ethics will not waver at mixing the honey with sugar
syrup. They need the money and people are not willing to compensate them
fairly for real honey. They could take another path and just not sell
the honey, keep it for themselves. But unfortunately, we can’t survive
on just honey.<br />
Is this wrong? Is this right? Unfortunately, this is just life. Of
course, it has something to do with capitalism but not as much as we’d
like to think. People have always operated first and foremost in
self-interest.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1685773253905-915ce8dd470b?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw0M3x8aG9uZXl8ZW58MHx8fHwxNzMxMjEzNTc4fDA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="a close up of a piece of food" />
<em>Photo by Lin Dai on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="beyond-the-jar-ethics-in-a-world-of-substitutes">Beyond the Jar: Ethics in a World of Substitutes</h2>

<p>As Aristotle once observed:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“To give away money is an easy matter and in any man’s power. But to decide
to whom to give it, and how large, and when, and for what purpose and how,
is neither in every man’s power nor an easy matter.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Similarly, to produce purely for profit is simple; to
balance ethics with survival is infinitely more complex.</p>

<p>We as human beings have an innate drive for survival and whatever the
circumstances, we will push, with an extra force, at our conditions in
order to survive. We are never completely independent so we will also
make great strides to make sure those dependent on us also survive. To
fault any person for cutting corners in the attempt to make a living, to
prolong their existence, is in my opinion an immoral act.</p>

<p>We often make this judgement from a place of safety and relative
affluence. Clearly, we who judge people of cutting corners, do not have
to do so ourselves. This means our survival is guaranteed enough that
don’t have to push against circumstance. However, we falsely project our
conditions onto those who are facing an entirely different reality. It’s
something to think about because in our daily lives we are not exposed
to the struggles and challenges of the lives of others. That, too, is
normal.</p>

<p>Consider the bee colony itself: when resources are scarce, they don’t
compromise on the quality of their honey—they simply produce less. But
they don’t have mouths to feed beyond their hive, no children to send to
school, no landlords demanding rent. Their economics is pure, while ours
is muddied by the complexity of human needs and desires.</p>

<p>I will leave you with a quote by Oscar Wilde that not only exemplifies
my point but adds to it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Selfishness is not living as one wishes to live, it is asking others
to live as one wishes to live. And unselfishness is letting other
people’s lives alone, not interfering with them. Selfishness always aims
at creating around it an absolute uniformity of type. Unselfishness
recognizes infinite variety of type as a delightful thing, accepts it,
acquiesces in it, enjoys it. It is not selfish to think for oneself. A
man who does not think for himself does not think at all. It is grossly
selfish to require of one’s neighbor that he should think in the same
way, and hold the same opinions. Why should he? If he can think, he will
probably think differently. If he cannot think, it is monstrous to
require thought of any kind from him. A red rose is not selfish because
it wants to be a red rose. It would be horribly selfish if it wanted all
the other flowers in the garden to be both red and roses.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>― <strong>Oscar Wilde, <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/66058139">The Soul of Man &amp; Prison
Writings</a></strong></p>

<p>In the end, perhaps the story of honey is the story of all things pure
in an impure world. The question isn’t whether everything is for sale,
but whether anything can remain pure by the very markets meant to
distribute it. Like the bees themselves, we must find a way to balance
the collective good with individual necessity. As we seek answers, we
might find wisdom in observing the bees themselves: they take only what
they need and give back more than they take.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Searching for pure honey revealed a bitter truth about our modern markets: 75% of retail honey is adulterated with sugar syrup. The honey seller faces an impossible choice—produce 100 genuine jars or 500 fake ones to meet demand. This isn't just about honey; it's about how our free market system has created more illusion than opportunity, forcing survival ethics that compromise authenticity. When everything has a price, what happens to purity?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Origins Of Social Inequality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/13/origins-of-social-inequality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Origins Of Social Inequality" /><published>2025-08-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/13/origins-of-social-inequality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/13/origins-of-social-inequality/"><![CDATA[<p>By Anubhav Kandpal</p>

<h2 id="why-this-is-not-the-right-question-to-ask">Why this is not the right question to ask</h2>

<p>What seems to be a common question has its roots in a phenomenon that is
rarely spoken of. This question was posed to the general public in 18th
century France as an essay competition. The winner was a certain
Jean-Jacques Rousseau whose essay explored a theme that was part social
critique, part biblical narrative and part thought experiment. He spoke
of mankind having lived most of prehistory in hunter-gatherer bands
where societies were more or less egalitarian. Humans had no need,
according to Rousseau, for creating complex social structures or
dominance hierarchies of arbitrary power. He then takes a biblical dive
depicting the fall of man and the rise of private property. The complex
social structures mankind experiences today are a product of the
evolution, enlightenment and development of modern man. His essay made
Rousseau famous and till today it is analysed and cited as a source of
social and political critique.</p>

<p>But, let’s hang on a minute. After all, this was an essay written for a
competition. In the essay he admits several times that his words are not
to be taken seriously for they are thought experiments in the history of
mankind. But the curious question is, how did this question get asked in
the first place?</p>

<p>In their recent book, <em>The Dawn of Everything</em>, Graeber and Wengrow talk
about this phenomena and what it means for the question – what are the
origins of social inequality. For this we have to go back to 1754 where
the <em>Académie des Sciences, Arts et Belles-Lettres de Dijon</em> announced
an essay competition on the question: “what is the origin of inequality
among men, and is it authorised by natural law?” The authors researched
why this was an appropriate question for a group of scholars to ask in
the first place.</p>

<p>The trail led them to rise of European colonialism where a few powerful
kings suddenly found themselves in control of vast stretches of Earth.
This was in the 1700s where European intellectuals were just
rediscovering Aristotle and the ancient world and were in a knowledge
bubble, unaware what people were thinking elsewhere. The discovery and
interaction with China, India and South America introduced new and
unimagined social, scientific and political ideas. This flood of new
ideas came to be known as the “Enlightenment”.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1501724326152-7a82bf5eae72?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw5fHxuYXRpdmUlMjB3aXNkb218ZW58MHx8fHwxNzMwOTg0ODEzfDA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="two white-blue-and-red teepee tents surrounded by green plants" />
<em>Photo by MJ Tangonan on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="when-worlds-collide-native-wisdom-meets-european-pride">When worlds collide: native wisdom meets European pride</h2>

<p>The founding of New France where the “civilised” French came into
contact with indigenous communities in the North American continent also
heralded a change in thought. What struck them was the way these
communities and societies were organised. They weren’t savages in a
“state of nature” or uncivilised, unruly and stupid people. On the
contrary, they were sophisticated and had organised their societies in a
different way, one where their inequalities were suppressed rather than
exaggerated. The conversations that took place between Europeans and
indigenous Americans about the nature of freedom, equality, rationality
and revealed religion were some of the themes that would feature
prominently in political thought during the Enlightenment.</p>

<p>Statesmen from these societies such as the Miq’mak and Algonkians, had
observed and interacted with the French and saw that their societies
functioned on the tenets of private property and arbitrary power.
Critiques of European institutions were surprisingly consistent among
various indigenous critics. These critiques started to be taken very
seriously in Europe. So much so that the fabric of European society
began to be called into question. This led to the emergence of a
pervasive narrative, which is now often taken as the standard narrative,
where individual freedoms are lost because societies grow bigger and
hierarchies and arbitrary power are natural consequences. This narrative
was developed to neutralise the indigenous critique among the European
society.</p>

<p>There was an underlying assumption in these narratives and Rousseau
about the state of nature. The assumption, whether we look at Hobbes or
Locke, was that humans existed as equals outside the confines of
civilisation. Equally good or equally bad? This varied from author to
author.</p>

<p>The issue with all these authors, namely Rousseau as the prime culprit
is the development of a narrative centred around the “stupid savage”.
That a human being outside civilisation is not civil, rational, logical
or capable of any independent thought. Hobbes” state of nature and the
“war of all, against all” exemplifies this more and more.</p>

<p>Where this narrative started from was a book called <em>Jesuit Relations of
New France</em>. Missionary and travel literature had become popular during
this time as a way for people to see that familiar ways of doing things
were not the only ways. Societies in existence that arranged themselves
differently were an inspiration to many key Enlightenment thinkers who
admit (and insist) that their ideals of individual liberty and political
equality were inspired by Native American sources and examples.</p>

<p>What we value today as personal freedom was to seventeenth-century
Jesuits scandalous. Father Lallemant who spoke with the Wendat in 1644
had this to say about them:<br />
<em>“I do not believe that there is any people on earth freer than they,
and less able to allow the subjection of their wills to any power
whatever - so much so that Fathers here have no control over their
children, or Captains over their subjects, or the Laws of the country
over any of them except in so far as each is pleased to submit to them.
There is no punishment which is inflicted on the guilty, and no criminal
who is not sure that his life and property are in no danger…”</em></p>

<p><em>Curious Dialogues with a Savage of Good Sense Who Has Travelled</em> was
written by Baron de Lahontan in 1703. He was French traveller who found
himself in New France and had learned a few indigenous languages and was
an intermediary for many years between the colonists and the natives.
His book is a series of dialogues between himself and Kandiaronk, a
Wendat statesman who takes a critical view of European society and its
ideas at the time. Lahontan claimed to have based the conversations in
the book on real life conversations he had with the eloquent Wendat
statesman at Michilimackinac and as authors Wengrow and Graeber, who
compiled this revealing research, point out “there is every reason to
believe the basic arguments were Kandiaronk’s own.”</p>

<h2 id="the-empire-strikes-back-how-europe-defended-its-ways">The empire strikes back: how Europe defended its ways</h2>

<p>An example of the way the Native Americans, who had been to France, saw
European society:</p>

<p>“They were continually teasing us with the faults and disorders they
observed in our towns, as being occasioned by money. There’s no point in
trying to remonstrate with them about how useful the distinction of
property is for the support of society: they make a joke of anything you
say on that account. In short, they neither quarrel nor fight, nor
slander one another; they scoff at arts and sciences and laugh at the
difference of ranks which is observed with us. They brand us for slaves,
and call us miserable souls, whose life is not worth having, alleging
that we degrade ourselves in subjecting ourselves to one man [the
King] who possesses all the power, and is bound by no law but his own
will.”</p>

<p>Along with criticisms such as the above on lack of mutual aid and blind
submission to authority, natives also criticised the organisation of
private property where Lahontan says: “They think it unaccountable that
one should have more than another, and that the rich should have more
respect than the poor. In short, they say, the name of savages, which we
bestow on them, would fit ourselves better since there is nothing in our
actions that bears an appearance of wisdom.”</p>

<p>Powerful words from a person who the French classified as a savage.
Kandiaronk’s arguments stemmed from the fact that material interests
were obstacles to some of the true values of humanity: “wisdom, reason,
equity…” among others. While indigenous societies were not totally
egalitarian, and the assertions of Kandiaronk were likely exaggerated
for effect, this was not the only reason his arguments were dismissed.
Scholars were ready to believe and insisted that Kandiaronk and his
critique were entirely fabricated. They claimed no such person ever
existed.</p>

<p>This psychological tendency to define ourselves in opposition to
others - <strong>Schismogenesis</strong> - helps explain why European intellectuals
found it so difficult to accept indigenous critiques: acknowledging the
wisdom in Native American social organization would have meant
questioning their own society’s supposed superiority.</p>

<p>Similar patterns emerged in British India, where colonial administrators
encountered sophisticated traditions that challenged their philosophical
assumptions about civilization. The British were particularly struck by
village-based democratic systems and communal property arrangements.
Warren Hastings, the first Governor-General of India, noted with
surprise how local panchayats (village councils) maintained order
without central authority. Meanwhile, Indian intellectuals like Ram
Mohan Roy pointed out the contradictions in European claims to
superiority, highlighting how British individualism and property rights
often led to social breakdown rather than progress. This parallel
critique from the East reinforced what Native Americans were saying in
the West - that perhaps European “civilization” wasn’t as advanced as it
claimed to be.</p>

<p>Another “put down” argument came from A.R.J. Turgot who acknowledged the
growing interest in the idea of freedom and equality but urged readers
to consider a larger context. He asserted that the freedom and equality
of savages was not a sign of their superiority but a sign of their
inferiority, since “it is only possible in a society where everyone is
equally poor.” Turgot theorised that “we progress from simple societies
like those of the Wendat to our own complex commercial civilisation, in
which the poverty and dispossession of some is nonetheless the necessary
condition for the prosperity of society as a whole.”</p>

<p>So Turgot took the opposite stance to Rousseau where he envisioned
mankind in a “state of nature” as hierarchical and inherently unequal.
Turgot would later on speak elaborately on these ideas in lectures on
world history. His breakdown of societal progress into four stages was
borrowed by his friend and Scottish economist Adam Smith. How curious
that such ideas inspired the person who laid the foundations of economic
free market theory.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1585064210818-8b7af20d03b4?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHw2fHxjaGFuZ2V8ZW58MHx8fHwxNzMwOTQyMTcwfDA&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="black and white wall mounted paper" />
<em>Photo by Markus Spiske on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="breaking-free-rethinking-how-we-live-together">Breaking free: rethinking how we live together</h2>

<p>Coming back to Rousseau we see his model of human society, which lived
free in bands of hunter-gatherers and avoided each other for fear of
violence, was something he emphasised was not to be taken seriously. But
it was. Rousseau was a crucial figure in the formation of left-wing
thought. In the mid eighteenth century the political “left” and “right”
themselves did not yet exist. They originally referred to the respective
seating positions of aristocratic and popular factions in the French
National Assembly of 1789.</p>

<p>Rousseau, with his essay, essentially reduced people outside European
society, or savages, to people without any imaginative powers of their
own; that their happiness is entirely derived from their inability to
imagine things otherwise, or to project themselves into the future in
any way at all; as a people completely lacking in philosophy. In this
way, the authors of the <em>Dawn of Everything</em>, accuse Rousseau of a
fundamental crime – that of the proclamation of the “myth of the stupid
savage.” Even if he imagined these savages to be blissful in their
stupidity.</p>

<p>The contrast between European and indigenous worldviews is perhaps best
captured in poetry. William Blake, writing in the midst of European
“civilization,” observed:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Pity would be no more<br />
If we did not make somebody poor;<br />
And Mercy no more could be<br />
If all were as happy as we.</p>

  <p>Mutual fear brings peace,<br />
Till the selfish loves increase:<br />
Then Cruelty knits a snare,<br />
And spreads his baits with care.</p>

  <p>He sits down with holy fears,<br />
And waters the ground with tears;<br />
Then Humility takes its root<br />
Underneath his foot.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While centuries later, Joy Harjo of the Muscogee Creek Nation would
write:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Remember the earth whose skin you are:<br />
red earth, black earth, yellow earth, white earth<br />
brown earth, we are earth.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These voices, separated by time and culture, speak to fundamentally
different ways of seeing human society - one highlighting the artificial
creation of inequality, the other reminding us of our fundamental
interconnectedness.</p>

<p>Moving from poetry to anthropological analysis, these historical debates
find fascinating supporters in modern research. Modern anthropologists
have discovered that many hunter-gatherer societies actively maintain
equality through what they call “reverse dominance hierarchies” - where
the group works together to ensure no individual gains too much power.
Studies of contemporary egalitarian societies show sophisticated methods
for maintaining balance: excessive boasting might be met with public
mockery, successful hunters are required to share their catch with
specific family groups, and important decisions must be reached through
group consensus rather than individual authority. A successful hunter
who becomes arrogant might find himself the subject of playful mimicry
around the evening fire, his boasts transformed into community
entertainment until the lesson in humility is learned.</p>

<p>A French anthropologist in the 1960s called Pierre Clastres suggested
the opposite. He questioned the standard narrative: “What if the sort of
people we like to imagine as simple and innocent are free of rulers,
governments, bureaucracies, ruling classes and the like, not because
they are lacking in imagination but because they’re actually <em>more</em>
imaginative that we are?” Although his argument has its limits, it
reminds us that we have difficulty in imagining what a free society
looks like but we have no difficulty imagining what arbitrary power and
domination look like. It could be probably that these indigenous
societies were the same and far from only imagining arbitrary power and
domination, they arrange their societies in such a way as to consciously
avoid it. He insisted that the people studied by an anthropologist are
just as self-conscious, just as imaginative as the anthropologist
themselves.</p>

<p>What all this aims to suggest is that a question seeking the “origins of
social inequality” will have to also confront the “origins of
civilisation” and a plethora of questions that seek to clarify what kind
of equality we are talking about. As we know the standard narrative we
have grown up with and carry in our school textbooks is one where we see
ourselves as the proud product of civilisation and progress. We see
ourselves as higher than those without civilisation. The ranking exists
blatantly in the way the world is split. First-world countries and
Third-world countries separate the colonisers from the colonised. But
are we really still harbouring that kind of mentality?</p>

<p>Is our future to be determined by the prejudiced opinion of past
scholars who, for better or for worse, never had to really face life
outside their so called civilisation? There is no short answer for the
origins of civilisation or for the origins of social inequality but the
seeking of a short answer will land us into trouble and keep us confined
to a narrative that disadvantages certain communities and even certain
aspects of our own nature.</p>

<p>We are all <em>Homo Sapiens</em> and the difference between us are not as large
as they used to be approximately 40,000-60,000 years ago. If we are to
truly understand ourselves then we could best see all societies as
equally unequal and that since the dawn of mankind, we have found
different and creative ways to organise ourselves. That maybe this
“state of nature” we so readily put prehistoric man in, is nothing but
an argument that gives us comfort and helps us avoid facing certain
facts about a society that could be arranged differently.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How did the question of social inequality become so central to our thinking? In 1754, European intellectuals encountered indigenous critics who challenged their assumptions about civilization, freedom, and hierarchy. Native American leaders like Kandiaronk questioned why Europeans accepted poverty and arbitrary power when more egalitarian societies existed. What followed was a defensive narrative that dismissed these critiques—leading to today's myths about 'primitive' societies and the inevitability of inequality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/12/beauty/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty" /><published>2025-08-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-08-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/12/beauty</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/08/12/beauty/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-ever-present-beauty">The Ever-Present Beauty</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Beauty is truth, truth beauty, —that is all
Ye know on earth, and all ye need to know.”
— John Keats, “Ode on a Grecian Urn”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There is beauty in this world. For those who have the eyes to see, it is
always there. It appears clear, unobstructed and pure. The beauty of
life is not to be lost in its trivialities, nor in its ceaseless
movement. But sadly, it often is. When we have lost the perception of
beauty in its wholeness, we find ourselves looking for it in
appearances. We start looking for the shine on the surface.</p>

<p>Beauty is always there, waiting for our eyes to notice. Zooming into
life magnified we see beauty creating an experience of the wonderous,
the sublime. As I sit in a hostel in Mexico, I could see myself as
someone who cannot write here, for this environment is chaotic, loud and
does not inspire the calm I need to write; but there is beauty in this
moment for I am around people—during a pandemic where many of us are
isolated—who have their own lives, are living their own struggles,
dreams, hopes and fears. They are all in this movement of life and when
you are in the thick of it, there is nothing to stop you from feeling it
all.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1501644898242-cfea317d7faf?crop=entropy&amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;fit=max&amp;fm=jpg&amp;ixid=M3wzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxNHx8YmVhdXR5JTIwcHJpc29ufGVufDB8fHx8MTczMTAzODU1OHww&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;q=80&amp;w=1080" alt="woman peeking over green leaf plant taken at daytime" />
<em>Photo by Drew Dizzy Graham on Unsplash</em></p>

<h2 id="the-prison-of-our-own-making">The Prison of Our Own Making</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We don’t see things as they are, we see them as we are.”
— Anaïs Nin</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When others look at me, they confine me to be only what they can
understand me to be. What I understand myself to be is unknown, profound
and ever-changing. However, when I feel confined to a persona, I become
concrete, known, heavy and an entity that is fixed. Change is not part
of how we perceive identity. It is static and a feeling of being someone
in a snapshot of time, or time in a snapshot as this person. We often
take the snapshot for the movie.</p>

<p>Just like we are conditioned to give ourselves and others a fixed
identity, we also do the same with experiences, observations and things.
Since we have become used to seeing ourselves as fixed beings who do not
change and are static, we give the same qualities over to what we
observe and identify with. A landscape becomes a photo on Instagram, an
object becomes just what we use it for and experiences become memories
which we use to escape the low-grade misery of our lives. We are
reducing everything dynamic, ever-changing and fluid to something that
is static, fixed and tangible. We are reducing all that is alive to all
that is dead. In this process of objectification, not only do we lose
contact with a living essence but we also become blind to real beauty.</p>

<p>The ancient Greeks knew something of this. Plato spoke of how everything
we see in our world is but a shadow of its perfect form. Like how all
the chairs we sit on are imperfect copies of the ideal chair that exists
in a realm of pure forms. But perhaps we have misunderstood this wisdom.
Maybe these perfect forms are not fixed ideals we should measure things
against, but rather the living essence that flows through all things.
When we see a chair, we can see just the wood and nails, or we can see
the beauty of human creativity meeting natural materials in an eternal
dance of form and function. Of course this is an exaggeration but for
purposes of argument it must be done.</p>

<h2 id="beyond-the-surface">Beyond the Surface</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Everything is blooming most recklessly; if it were voices instead of
colours, there would be an unbelievable shrieking into the heart of the
night.”
— Rainer Maria Rilke, “Letters on Cézanne”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So how do we find this beauty? Because it does not lie in identity nor
in identification. Real beauty lies in appreciation of the unknown, the
unexplainable nature of all we experience. Somehow it transcends our
rational understanding of the world, invoking a sense of awe and wonder
into our souls. When we are in this awe, we do not find an object or an
identification with anything but rather we find an experience—moving,
flowing and changing. It is these qualities of experience that make it
beautiful and it is our capitalist tendency to commodify experiences
that kill the beauty in them.</p>

<p>The experience of beauty can only be dulled by our expectations and our
explanations. Like a magic trick loses its brilliance when explained,
the intellectual understanding of experiences of beauty seems to dull
them down into a lower form of an experience. Why lower? Because it has
been taken from the whole and reduced to its parts. While there is
nothing inherently depreciating about this, experience is the whole and
analysis reduces it to its parts. How we feel about our bodies comes
from how all its parts are working together to create the sensation we
call health. When a part of our bodies like the stomach, brain, eyes,
nose and so on, don’t work as they could then we have a feeling of
uneasiness. We call this dis-ease. While disease is not a necessarily
beautiful experience it can lead to such and while health can behold
beauty, we forget to perceive it as such.</p>

<p>The heart knows beauty most deeply when it has known suffering. Like how
stars are most brilliant in the darkest night, or how a single flower
growing through concrete can move us more than a whole garden. There is
something profound in how suffering clears our eyes to see beauty more
purely. The mother who has known loss loves more fiercely. The artist
who has known emptiness creates more truthfully. The traveller who has
known loneliness sees the beauty in small connections more clearly.
Perhaps this is why beauty can bring tears to our eyes - because it
touches both the light and shadow within us, reminding us that neither
exists without the other.</p>

<h2 id="the-eye-that-sees-beauty">The Eye That Sees Beauty</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The moment one gives close attention to anything, even a blade of
grass, it becomes a mysterious, awesome, indescribably magnificent world
in itself.”
— Henry Miller</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The movement of the clouds and the way the blue sky plays hide and seek
with our eyes, dancing with different shades in the hue of the clouds.
If we really look, we can see beauty in that. A complex and contrasting
landscape of colours and shapes always changing above us with light that
is not blue but seems to appear so just to delight our eyes, can it
really get better than this? But this same scene can be seen as ordinary
and as something that’s just ‘whatever’. And so we realise the maxim is
true, beauty does indeed lie in the eye of the beholder.</p>

<p>In such a case, is there something to be said for cultivating this eye
of being able to perceive beauty in its wholeness? Unclouded by
perceptions, judgements and opinions this eye can see all as pure and
seemingly perfect. I can only talk for myself when I see the beauty in
life. Walking around in Oaxaca city—a city unknown to me—I do not seek
the experience of a tourist, rather I notice the way houses are made,
their designs and how they seem to just come together to form this city
to give it its unique allure. The shapes of different streets uniquely
marking the blood vessels of this city. Since my eyes are seeing all
this anew, I cannot take this for granted.</p>

<p>As I write this, I look in front of me at a green courtyard full of
plants, grass and a remaining essence that makes it seem like it comes
from antiquity. The big white fluffy clouds dance above me and peeking
from behind them is the deep blue sky. On the roof of this courtyard
sits a deep blue water tank and whether by design or coincidence, the
blue of the water tank almost exactly matches that of the sky peeking
behind the clouds. This is my experience of beauty in the small everyday
moments of life. In such a way, whether it is the streets, or the clouds
or the children in the park, beauty is not an isolated experience. It is
an exquisite melange of coinciding factors that make it mysteriously
alluring and forever fascinating.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>When we truly see beauty,
Time stands still like morning dew
Suspended on a blade of grass
Neither falling nor rising
Just being, in perfect presence
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Anubhav Kandpal</name></author><category term="beauty" /><category term="consciousness" /><category term="perception" /><category term="awareness" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="aesthetics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Beauty is always present, waiting for eyes that can truly see beyond surface appearances. Yet we often imprison ourselves and others in fixed identities, reducing dynamic experiences to static snapshots. Real beauty lies not in identification but in appreciation of the unknown—it transcends rational understanding and can only be dulled by our expectations. Can we cultivate the eye that perceives beauty in wholeness, unclouded by judgments?]]></summary></entry></feed>